Heat. Heat. N.
[Music]
Come
down.
[Music]
Heat. Heat.
Hello and good evening, good day
everybody and welcome to the 259th
episode of the Ask Vija show. Hope
everybody is doing great. Let's see who
all is there on the live chat with us.
Let us see. I can see hersi dic shrian
samarati de kaiser s jooshi somia dikit
geopolitical dub from indor
slayer shashank koshik du durya durya
mei lagot anonymous scientist happy
birthday sir uh sonuharav Mr. Long's
chlong din kamat rishi sate Mr. 88ers
geopolitical again push raana Mr. Ra Mr.
Jam Hitanchu Meta Shri Ram Chandra
Namaha Slayer Shiva Daran S Praal from
Kolkata. Uh who else? Sadhart Sharma
Slayer Dipti Talle Pushutam Pradhan. Uh
who else? Rajesh Daswani
and Yatesh Jooshi Samatraati again Nandu
Lal Vikram Kadan best COC bases with
link likit shrinat
who is wondering if this is live well
what can I say uh sai sumant event
countdown or aul
alchemist mystic skitumar sahil singh
oju iklavia ei shif patel priyanka
javalia suryan An Kapil
Ashoto Sapati Susant Patil Abin of
Mishra Bay Mr. Didi uh W co Anulik Ajin
Kapawar Vikash PJ Baron Zemo Makleven
from Superbad Gorav Gupta Anudip Tasin
Amisha Mishra hello Duta Arindam Roy Jay
Guman Shrira Anand Padma Yat Giri So
Jooshi and so many other so many other
people. So thank you so much all of you
for being on the live chat and let us
get going with some questions. What
questions do we have?
uh unknown says best way to read foreign
record for our society is there's a
series of books by Dr. Minaki Jay in
which she's written about what
foreigners have written about India so
she's compiled all of that in a multi-
volume source so it's a set of books by
Dr. oxygen. You can check that out.
That's a good that's a good source for
what you're looking for.
Um Prashant says distorted maps of India
for example flight aware etc. Solution
solution means you actually recti
rectify the problem on the ground. The
world will keep on doing this. The only
way if we to solve this is to change the
facts on the ground. Okay, that's it.
That's it. If if some other country
think about it if let's say Argentina
says that Faulland Islands is is malinas
and it belongs to me do we care
we only care about who actually
possesses what and that's how it should
be so Indians should uh develop a
thicker skin the world is going to be
like this okay to solve this problem we
have to change the facts on the ground
of course there are issues wherein we
have the facts on the ground and still
there are nations which would like to
you know portray things differently. For
example, Israel put out a map today or
yesterday in which they showed Arunachal
Pradesh is part of China even though
Arunachal Pradesh is very much part of
India and that these are the facts on
the ground and yet Israel put out a map
in which Arunachal Pradesh is a part of
China. So in this case well there's
nothing much we can do about what other
nations want but it tells you what their
true feelings for us are. Okay.
Pur Shotam says, "What's the update in
the Russia Ukraine war? Big fan. Thank
you, sir. Update is it's going on."
Okay. After the big uh developments a
couple of weeks ago of operation
spiderweb and various Ukrainian
long-range strikes into Russia and
Russian retaliation, beyond that it's
kind of again going back to normal. So
beyond that there's not a nothing major.
There's a Subie offensive and there are
there are some other offensives by
Russia on the ground. But it's going as
per things the way things have been
going for quite some time, you know. So,
nothing nothing major as an update.
Slayer says Iran Iran claims it shot
down two F-35 fighter jets. Your views,
I'll have to see the evidence. I've seen
some evidence that doesn't really look
like evidence. So, I don't know. I'm
going to reserve my judgment until we
find a definitive evidence or nothing
comes up.
Uh, Rahul says, "Thormet zeus push Ram
two thoughts." No thoughts.
Backbenture Academy lover says, "What's
the morning routine of a geopolitical
analyst?"
Uh, well, morning routines are secret. A
geopolitical a true geopolitical analyst
never reveals details of their routines.
You get it? Things are supposed to be
kept under wraps.
Vive Singh says, "Pra G, how do you see
the Middle East geopolitics going? Is it
is it is the time for for hardcore
Islamic nations over with Saudi and the
UAE leading the way? I think this is
nothing to do with Islam or not Islam or
any such thing. Okay. Uh Middle East
geopolitics.
Well, we know what's happening. The
Israelis did a decapitation strike on
top Iranian leadership. The Iranians
have responded in some way. They've uh
you know they they've launched various
kinds of missiles at Tel Aviv and other
places. Some of these have scored hits
despite the wonderful iron dome system.
Many of the missiles have been
intercepted and so on and so forth. This
has nothing to do with Islam. If this
had something to do with Islam, okay,
think about it. Indians, hello Indians.
Listen, listen up Indians. If you think
that this has to something to do with
Islam, let me point something out to
you. Indians don't like to think, right?
Let me make you think. If Israel has a
problem with Islam and they are doing
this because they are against Islam,
then why has Israel never done a thing
against Pakistan?
Israel keeps on claiming, my friends,
that Iran is the global epicenter of
terrorism, which is a lie. Okay, we know
it. It's not it's not it's not true.
Iran is not the global epicenter of
terrorism. Iran has never done any
terrorism against us. We know where the
global epicenter of terrorism is. It is
Pakistan
and Pakistan has nuclear weapons which
seem to be American nuclear weapons. Now
the question is why? I mean if I if
Israel is so much anti-terrorism, why
have they never done a thing against
Pakistan?
Ask yourselves this question my dear
friends.
This has nothing to do with Islam
and it's not over for hardcore Islamic
nations etc. It's things will keep
changing. Uh, it looks like it was the
West that that forced nations like Saudi
Arabia to become hardcore Islamic
nations, Islamic, Islamist, whatever
they call it. I have no idea what these
things mean, but whatever. And Saudi
Arabia would actually like to go back to
its more moderate version of Islam. I
mean, if you look at if you look at
photographs of the Arabian region, the
Saudi Arabian region from let's say the
late 1800s, early 1900s, etc., etc., you
will not see women wearing black burkas
and all that.
So th this changed because of the
influence of the west and now it's
changing again because the nations are
kind of to some extent reverting to
their true uh way of doing things.
So geopolitics in the Middle East right
now it's it's a mess. Uh it looks like
there is I've been saying this would
this could happen that the Israelis
could hit at uh could strike at Iranian
nuclear bases and and so on so forth
which seems to be happening right now.
It all depends on how Iran retaliates.
Does Iran retaliate? If it doesn't
retaliate, it loses all credibility and
it invites more Israeli uh strikes
because Israel would like to do a regime
change in Iran and and the Americans
would also like this very much. So then
the prospect is that there could be a
regime change in Iran. The current
regime of the moolas and goes and a pro-
US regime comes to power. Yes. Best
thing in the world, democracy, human
rights, blah blah blah. Right. Indians.
Worst thing for India.
Sergeant Skyland says, "I think India is
going for the SU57 deal. We'll have to
wait and watch. Uh I think we are
considering it pretty seriously, but we
still have to wait and watch. I think
it'll be a good thing if we go for the S
SU57 deal. There are many analysts who
are shilling for the F-35 that
overpriced
flying trash can. I think the SU57 is
better as long as we get to modify it,
augment it, integrate our systems into
it, I think it'll be a very good deal.
Right.
Indian media is calling out US pilots to
hear expert opinion on AI 171
uh indirectly saying pilot error to save
Boeing. If will we ever go get over this
brown koolie behavior? No. The Indian
media is full of brown kies. Okay, they
need white validation including people I
know very well. They need white
validation. A white guy needs to come
and tell them what have what must have
happened and then they are like ah let's
take this seriously.
So there is this this this some some
apparent expert who comes in dressed for
the occasion in in you know uh captain's
costume or whatever it is. Yeah. And
that guy is going around saying that
this was this this was pilot error that
instead of instead of pulling the wheels
up the the guy put the flaps down the
co-pilot or something like that and then
it was too late to change anything.
That's the claim the guy is making
complete speculation
but yes the Indian media especially some
utter brownies will call people like
that to spread their so-called expert
opinion. So this is a deeprooted problem
in India. It is not going to change
until the government of India bothers to
change the education system in a proper
way. It's not going to go away.
So what can I say? It's it's unfortunate
that we are in this situation.
Dendore, thank you so much and welcome
to membership. Thank you so much.
Sahil Patil says ideal stockpile for
India to become a superpower. Stockpile
of what? Stockpile of baby powder.
Johnson's baby powder. What are you
talking about? You're talking about
bullets, shells, missiles, helicopters.
You're talking about nuclear weapons.
What are you talking about? Uh nuclear
weapons? I think u
well
maybe 500.
Yeah, if you're talking about if you're
talking about nuclear weapons. But
beyond that, we need a proper stockpile
of delivery systems. It doesn't matter
if you have 100 or 10,000 nuclear
weapons and if you don't have the means
to deliver them. We need missiles of
various kinds. We need a huge stockpile
of missiles. Forget about the nuclear
stockpile. We need a stockpile of tens
of thousands of missiles of various
kinds. That's what we need. Then
everybody will be be beware of us
because we have the numerical ability to
to overwhelm many air defenses. We need
a stockpile of tens of thousands of
missiles.
MK says, why call regions as states when
it implies autonomy? Shouldn't we use
provinces to reflect one united nation
like China? We are using whatever the
British the whatever terms the British
used or did it or or are we are we? I
think the what did the British call our
our regions? Did they call them
provinces? Maybe they did. I I don't
know what made India choose the term
states because it does imply autonomy.
The nation state the state. Yes, it
does. Um we can use the word you know
why do we need to use English words? We
can use the word pr which is a Sanskrit
term which has none of the the autonomy
connotations.
So if you really want to decolonize you
can use your own
civilizational and and linguistic terms
use the word prant or something similar
or something that is appropriate for the
region I would say.
Vidi says, "Why is the Indian media's
representation misinformed and borish?"
Because these folks have no
understanding of anything. See, I'll
tell you what. Until the year 2020, we
used to have so-called strategic affairs
experts who would come on the Indian
media would typically be retired armed
forces personnel and they would talk
about Pakistan, Pakistan, Pakistan,
Pakistan. And the Indian media anchors,
the big big superstar anchors, they have
no understanding whatsoever of
geopolitics. Now in the past two years
they have got access to chart GBT. So
any media anchor suddenly can act like
an expert and give give guan but they
are they have they are clueless. They
don't have any background in this. They
have zero actual background depth of
understanding of of study in
geopolitics. They don't understand the
historical background. They don't
understand the cause and effect
causality. They don't understand the
chronology. They'll ask JB to something.
It'll give you a little list of bullet
points and that's it. Yes, these are our
topic talking points. Yes. And so on. So
it's idiotic. It's it's it's halfbaked.
It's very shallow. These people have no
real understanding of what the national
interest is. Deep national interest from
a geopolitical global integrated
perspective. That's why it's just noise
on Indian media. It's it's h yeah I'm
I'm it's very offputting.
When is episode two with French intel
RAM waiting? Well, it'll come when it
comes.
Uh, Sahil says, "Why secure Nepal in
Lanka if China invades Taiwan? Because
these are our our civilizational areas
and we cannot have the situation where
somebody gets a chance to intrude into
them.
For example, Sri Lanka, Alanka is pretty
much secure. It's uh on the southern
part of India. It's it's pretty secure
because there's no other nation that can
come and do a land grab. But Nepal, it's
between India and Chinese occupied
Tibet. So we really have to secure Nepal
if something happens. So it's you can't
just keep on losing territory. We have
been losing territory for the past 1,000
years.
We've been losing territory piece by
piece by piece by piece. We used to have
our footprint all the way up to Baku
Azarbaijan in Armenia and all the way to
Russia. We had Indians all over Central
Asia living all over all across Central
Asia. We can still see the
archaeological evidence of that. But
slowly slowly we have been retreating
retreating all over the place and now we
have even lost Gandhar and and Pakistan
so-called Pakistan. Nepal is no longer
part of India which is okay which is
okay. It is still independent and it is
still okay. We've lost East Bengal,
Bangladesh, Bangladesh and so much so
much more. We have been just retreating
retreating retreating.
If China invades Taiwan, it means that
they're in an expansionist mood. We have
to secure whatever we need to secure. So
that's why
um can India's doctrine change with a
new government at the center? If a new
government comes at the center,
everything will be 180 degrees U-turn.
Okay? If if it's the party that you're
thinking of. Um so yeah, of course it
can change. Nandanda Kizar is trying to
echo Elon Musk over here when Elon Musk
was talking about Trump. So anyway,
thank you sir.
Uh
geopolitical dub says PM Modi will
travel to Cypress. New grouping. Uh
well, I'm not aware of this new p piece
of news. If he does travel to Cypress,
I'm I welcome that. Cypress. Um Cypress
is interesting. It's an interesting
place. Half of Cypress, the northern
part is occupied by Turkey. Turkish
occupied Cypress. The south of south of
Cypress is still uh you know, it's still
autonomous. It is Cypress historically
was a Greek island. The Turks have taken
over about about half of the northern
part of the the northern part of the
island. It happened sometime in the
1970s. Okay. So if Prime Minister Modi
goes to Cypress, he's not going to the
northern half. I assure you of that.
He's going to go to the southern half of
Cyprus. And uh India is very much uh on
excellent terms with Greece and not with
Turkey. So we'll see. We seem to have
some kind of a quasi alliance kind of
situation going going on with Greece
which is great. It's something that's
happened after 2,300 years 2,500 years
almost. Yeah. So uh yeah we'll we'll
have to wait and watch but I am not
aware of this particular thing. It seems
to be a new piece of news.
Uh Vive Singh says any impact on the BLA
resistance of if Iran falls. Yeah that's
a good question. What could happen?
Maybe is the Balojasthan Liberation Army
possibly getting some support from
Persia, from Iran? Um, and what happens
if Iran falls, which means there's a
pro- US government that comes to power.
So if a pro- US regime puppet regime
comes to power in Iran, then it's going
to be very pro Pakistan because Pakistan
is also a US which means the two nations
could get together to the two regimes
the Pakistani dictatorship and the
Iranian uh pro- US regime could get
together and try to destroy the
Balojasthan Liberation Army. That's what
could happen right
hersa says from the land of the great
brahmacharis in Kamasutra to simple
capital of the world and second largest
corn consumption in the world is it due
to colonization or something else please
explain what has gone wrong it's a it's
because of the media exposure it's
because of what's being normalized in
India it's been happening very slowly
very subtly very insidiously started
with Bollywood
you know historically
I mean certain things were not part of
our culture but Bollywood has been
slowly steadily injecting that that rot
into our our our psyche our mindset
slowly gradually year after year decade
after decade has started it's probably
started sometime in the 1970s
that's almost 50 years ago for 50 years
they've been injecting this rot this
foreign garbage into into India now it
has gone all the way to to what we call
the OTT platforms and those third rate
uh cals that people watch as
entertainment and all of that is now
seen as normal whatever you're talking
about you know what they call in Hindi
ashila and all that there's a difference
between art and ashilta
in Indian art you can see all over
temples and all you had examples of
nudity which was normal in the old days
and now because of the foreign 1000
years of foreign occupation of India
women had to cover up so now that's the
new normal but Now people want to
represent the female form without
clothes in an in a vulgar way, not in an
artistic way, in a vulgar way. And
that's become normal now. It's very
normal, you know,
having lots of extra marital affairs and
promiscuity and all of that is normal in
your TV serals and all that stuff. So
people feel it's normal and it's now
becoming normal in society.
It is the media, it's the entertainment
industry etc. that have normalized all
this garbage, all this rot.
I am not saying people should cover up
and people should become brahmacharis
and all. Do live your life but live as
as as in in line with your
civilizational values.
Everything was allowed in our
civilization but promiscuity and all
this nonsense was never part of our
culture. But now it's become normal. We
are just trying to ape the west because
we have this deep inferiority complex.
Most Indians have it. They want to
whatever the white man does has to be
right. And we have to try and emulate
that to to become better to better
ourselves. So that's what's gone wrong.
The inferiority complex, the
entertainment industry, the media, even
the education system which which puts
the white man on a pedestal. All of this
come putting together coming together
has created this situation where we we
are we are a nation of utter losers and
simps. Full supports are
Mr. Strange says, "What's the stance of
Russia and China in the Israel Iran war?
They're going to stay out of it." You
see, I mean, it'll be a setback for
Russia if Iran falls. Um, but by now,
I'm sure they have localized the
production of Shahed 2 and Shahed
whatever drones and so on. So, they'll
be okay.
For China, it'll be a setback because
they have this 25 year strategic
agreement with Iran,
which essentially is Chinese attempt to
colonize Iran and to acquire great
quantities of very cheap, you know,
energy from Iran and all that. So, it'll
be a setback for Iran if it'll be a
setback for China as well as Russia if
Iran falls. But see what's happened is
this. because of the sudden flare up in
the West Asia region, uh the world's
eyes have gone off the the Ukraine
issue,
right? So, no one's talking about
Ukraine right now. The everyone's
looking at Israel and Iran. So, Russia
can quietly achieve certain certain ends
that they want right now in in Ukraine
without the the gaze of the world being
on that and uh so on. So it gives Russia
some breathing space to do what it
wants. But overall it will be bad for
Russia as well as China as well as for
India if the Iran uh if Iran underos a
regime change.
Priyal says why is the world on fire?
Well, we didn't start the fire. It's
been burning ever since the world's been
turning. What can I say?
Shaman Dubet says when the time when the
time truly comes, who will genuinely
stand with India? Some are already
questioning if this represents a failure
in our geopolitical strategy. Those who
say that this represents a failure in
our geopolitical strategy, they don't
know what geopolitics is. They have no
understanding of history. They have no
understanding of anything. They all they
want to do is to to throw some fuel in
the fire and and get some likes and and
shares and all that nonsense. H
India has always been alone
for decades for year for centuries for
centuries India has been alone. When the
time comes, nobody will stand with
India. Right now, Iran is under fire.
Who is standing with Iran? Tell me. Has
China come to Iran's rescue? Has Russia
come to Iran's rescue? If the regime is
overthrown in in Thran, is anybody
coming to Iran's rescue? Why do you
think it's only about India, India,
India? Everybody is on their own. If
something bad happens to the US
tomorrow, do you think that EU and NATO
is going to come to the rescue?
If something really bad happens,
nobody's going to come to the rescue to
hell with article this or that of the
NATO charter or whatever. Nobody's going
to come to the rescue. People come to
your rescue only if they fear you and if
they think that and if they think that
you know you're going to survive
whatever is happening.
So the this alliance that the Americans
have created, NATO, North Atlantic
Treaty Organization, this alliance, it
will work as long as the NATO nations
fear the US. If the US becomes genuinely
very weak and it's under siege and it's
it's in danger of going down like they
say NATO will automatically dissolve.
Nobody will come to the US's rescue. So
please understand that there are no
friends in geopolitics.
It's always alliances and and agreements
and arrangements of convenience.
Even when you have shared civilizational
interests and all even then people won't
come with you come come and stand with
you and put put their put their necks on
the line if if if it comes to that think
back of the old days when these Goris
and Gaznavis used to invade India at
that time India was not unified under a
single geopolitical entity like an
emperor right so the the Gori or Gnavi
would invade one kingdom one Rajput
kingdom and everybody around the other
kingdoms nearby were all also Rajput
kingdoms but they would say okay it's
not happening to me it's happening to
him uh maybe it will not happen to me
let's stay away that's how it works what
happens locally also applies globally so
when the time truly comes nobody is
going to stand with us and that's
nothing unique nobody's stand with
standing with Iran right now tomorrow if
something bad happens to China do you
think anybody will stand with China
h nobody will when things went bad bad
when when everything went wrong with
Iraq Iraq with Saddam Hussein. Who stood
with Saddam Hussein? Tell me when
Gaddafi was overthrown. Who stood with
Libya?
Come on. It's the That's the way it is
all across the world. Why are we
thinking that we are something if the
whole world is against us? It's nothing
to do with the whole world being against
us at all. That's just the way the world
works. This is nothing to do with the
failure of Mr. Modi's geopolitical
strategy. Only 30 IQ people are saying
that. Okay.
So we are on our own and we have to
ensure that nobody can you know dare try
to cross us. That's what I say. That's
what I would say.
Sid says how can grassroots thought
leaders and families help elevate
discourse and foster an indic.
The grassroots efforts are all going to
be mediocre. Okay. There are so many
so-called grassroots efforts. this
organization that organization I'm not
naming anybody by the way I'm just
talking saying in general lots of
initiatives here and there do are
occurring but what greatness do you see
in them
greatness can only be applied to a
civilization top down never bottom up
bottom up is always going to be average
stuff average people doing average
things
there are no grassroot thought leaders I
cannot think of
Um and it's it's look every every great
leader who becomes a great person does
come from the grassroots at some point
in time but first they have to elevate
themselves above the grassroots and you
know find a way find a way of of rising
and becoming very prominent becoming a
colossus it's only then then you that
you can change things elevate discourse
foster an indicance first of all without
large amounts of money. There's going to
be no elevation of discourse and no
indicance.
The word renaissance comes from what
happened in Europe about 500 or so years
ago. How did the renaissance come about?
It came about because of of a tremendous
amount of prosperity.
It was money
that fueled the renaissance. It was
prosperity and money excess money that
proc that that that fueled the
renaissance. Do we have that in India
right now? First of all, India needs to
become super prosperous or at least
moderately prosperous so that some
people have the excess money and they
have the right mindset to maybe use that
money to create some kind of artistic
renaissance, cultural renaissance and so
so forth. Right? Such people are never
grassroots leaders. Such people are
always hired than grassroots.
Any person who is exceptional is by
definition not a grassroots person. That
person is always different. That person
stands apart. that person doesn't belong
with the average people. The average
people don't understand such people.
You've got to be different. If you are
the same as everybody else, there's
nothing you're going to be able to do
because you're going to think the same
way as everybody else. So my point is if
some of you want to bring about an
indicance,
think different. Don't be like everybody
else. Don't be average. Don't be
mediocre. Mediocre means average. Don't
be average. Don't expect the world to
understand you.
Generate a lot of employment. Make a lot
of money. become super prosperous and
then you can do it top down, not bottom
up. That's what you need to do because
I've seen lots of these bottom up
organizations and all. They do nothing.
They do nothing. They they they have no
impact on on the world unfortunately.
Divium says, "What's the what's the
major source of your income?" Well, that
is classified and that's not for you to
know, sir.
Confused fan says Elon Musk replied to a
user who was talking about how by using
Starink they can use they can do a
regime change in Iran. Why are we
allowing Starling in India? It's because
we have somehow been arm twisted into
doing this. It is it goes completely
against our national interest. I would
still urge the government of India to
undo to revoke the license for Starlink.
Starlink is going to be a national
security threat. It's going to be a
sovereignty threat threat for India.
We remember right Donald Trump put out
this tweet a month ago that he used the
he used the threat of sanctions economic
sanctions on on India to stop India from
destroying Pakistan. He must have used
such such similar threats to force India
to agree to giving to give Starlink a
license. Right now Elon Musk and Donald
Trump are fighting. Maybe it's the right
it's the right time for us to revoke the
license. But that time will not last
forever. If you want the right time
window, the right right time window is
now. I would urge the government of
India to revoke Starlink's license. We
don't need this this this third rate
service in India. We have excellent
internet services in India. Better than
most of the rest of the world. We don't
need Starlink. If you need something
like Starlink, create your own Starlink.
Don't you have some some selfrespect?
Use ISRO, use Gio, use Adani, use
whatever. have them create the bunch of
satellites 10,000 satellites and have a
launch them make this happen in the next
five years. Why can't we do it? Of
course, it can be done and then we can
compete with Starlink and out compete
Starlink. That's what needs to happen
ideally but let's see.
Godliness says can you enlighten the
Indians and the policy makers on the
dangers of drying rivers, extreme heat
waves, decreasing agricultural land,
soil erosion these problems are huge.
These problems are huge. I agree.
What? See, heat waves,
they dry out our soil. They dry out our
agricultural land. It's climate change.
Our crops,
they need certain kinds of climates and
certain kinds certain kinds of weather
patterns, right? Because they've evolved
like to to to make use of these
patterns, these climatic patterns over
tens of thousands of years.
We have been doing agriculture in India
for at least 17 18,000 years. Ever since
then the the crop crops are used these
they are accustomed to these climatic
patterns. Now if the climate changes
it's going to cause it's going to be
disastrous. If the temperature rises by
two two degrees that could destroy crops
it could make us dependent on crops on
on imports from other parts of the world
right um you see drying rivers all over
the place. You open Google maps and on
on the on the map it'll be shown as a
blue line but when you see the satellite
image it's all dried out. You see that
all over the place. Uh
so yes, extreme heat waves again they
they cause a tremendous amount of
damage. They destroy crops. They kill
people. They kill animals. They destroy
agricultural land because of extreme
heat. You know the green cover of of the
country starts reducing. Because of that
there is soil erosion. The the top soil
flies away which makes the soil barren
and so on. These problems are huge.
What's the solution? We can talk about
problems all day, all day, all day, all
day. What's the solution to these
problems? The solution is that we need
to reforest as much of our land as
possible. We need to reforest the hills
where there are no buildings, no
construction, if it's public land, if
it's government land, build forest, grow
forests all over the place. Uh we need
to ensure that rivers keep on flowing.
We should not build too many dams. We
should build dams strategically for for
sure. We need water to reach
agricultural lands all over the place.
We need to build more dams on the indust
river systems. No question about that.
No question. But we should build dams
strategically. Not should not cause
damage to the existing um you know
ecosystem and all ecosystems and all
that. So yeah, the problems are huge.
The solution is simple, easy to say but
difficult to do but which is to reforest
as much of our land as possible.
MK says, "Why did Chia dare to confront
the USSR during the Usuri River clashes
despite being isolated from the west and
knowing that the Soviets had nuclear
superior superiority?"
Okay. Uh this happened in the late 1960s
sometime in 1969. By the time China also
had I think the nuclear nuclear bomb,
but I think the Soviets had a
significant nuclear advantage. No
question about it. Now what happened was
this. At that time, the leader of China
was Mao Satung.
Maoadong was a huge admirer of Stalin,
Joseph Stalin. Okay. Mao sought st saw
Stalin as somebody who was superior to
him. He genuinely revered Joseph Stalin.
Now Stalin dies. Stalin died and then
Nikita Kruef became the next leader of
the USSR and Mao interacted with Nikita
Kushv etc. And Mao was not impressed at
all with Nikita Kruef. He he saw Nikita
Krishv as somebody not worthy of being
the successor of Stalin and he saw he
Mao could see the decline of the USSR
beginning with with Nikita Krishv. So he
lost respect for Krishv. He lost by
extension respect for the USSR
and he Mao always had this expansionist
nature. You know what he did with Tibet?
He grabbed such a huge territory because
we allowed him to do that. We we helped
him in doing that. So then he thought
let me try my luck with the USSR and try
and grab certain territories which
according to so and so ancient Chinese
map which I invented last last week is
was was part of our territory. So he
tried to grab some territory which was
kind of gray area gray zone kind of
thing not properly demarcated and that's
why you had the Usuri river clashes
which were tremendous clashes hundreds
of soldiers died and Nikita Krishv
decided that we will let us nuke
let us nuke China. So the Soviets had
nuclear superiority but the Chinese had
population superiority. Understand that
the Chinese used at in those days human
wave tactics uh in warfare just large
you know file after file of of human
beings soldiers with with these uh
primitive guns who would just walk or
run in in in lines you know in files. So
human wave tactics they had and the USSR
was rightfully concerned that Siberia
was next was almost empty and the so the
Chinese could just push in millions of
people into Siberia and just like that
take over Siberia. So there was a big
fear the the Soviets had about China and
that's the Chinese were aware of this
advantage of theirs. So that's why they
thought let's gamble and let's try and
grab some piece of some pieces of Soviet
territory and that's why this happened
and China must have gambled that maybe
the USSR will not use nuclear weapons on
us. They ch they decided to use the
weapons but the Americans came to know
about this and the Americans saved the
Chinese and that's how the whole process
of America start aiding and abetting and
midwifing China's rise all of that
starts over there
okay Chib says I'm 20 years old and I
failed in neat again please guide uh
you're 20 years old ne you failed okay
it's not the end of the world you can
try it again but you should also know
that you should not keep on trying this
over and over again in in case it's too
tough an exam for you. It's poss it's
possible. Nothing wrong with that. So,
first thing is don't get discouraged.
It's not the end of the world. You're
just 20. You're just starting your life.
There's so many options in front of you.
The younger you are, the more options
you have. The older you are, the less
options you have. So, at this point in
time, you're starting off, you have
options. So, don't get discouraged.
Maybe you can try it again if if it is
something you can do. Uh listen, I am
not that very well versed with the
Indian education system. It's something
I despise the education system. It's
terrible. It's rotten. But yes, people
like you, kids, I understand. You have
to use this to advance in life and start
some career. So, I would say listen,
don't get discouraged. It's not the end
of the world. Don't worry about what
people say about this. Oh, you failed or
whatever to hell with them. Who cares?
Uh if you really want, if this is
something that you really want, maybe
you can try again. Or maybe you should
have some plan B, plan C also along with
that. So, in case this doesn't work out,
what other things can you do? That's
what I would say you should do. Be
positive, be optimistic, be full of
energy, try again and and always have
plan B and plan C in case it doesn't
work out. So all the best. Yraj
Kiran Media says IDF still has not taken
the distorted Indian map down yet on
Twitter. They are sorry that they
revealed the true intentions. Well,
that's how it goes. Look, I have been
saying this for a long time. Israel is
not some special friend of India. We
have a lot of geopolitical convergence
of interests and that's why we work
together. Uh but you and we we have
developed various weapon systems with
Israel like the barak missile system. We
have we used the Israeli harup system.
Uh when the during the cargill war
Israel supported India Israel supplied
India with arms, ammunition whatever
that's what one hears and so on. They
sold it. They did not give it for free.
Please understand that. But the
Americans wanted India to do very poorly
but Israel kind of sold it to us.
Outstanding, good. But understand the
thing is unconditional. They're not like
some all-weather friends of ours. They
have their own interests. We have our
own interests. We have to understand
that our interests can differ in various
things. For example, when it comes to
voting in the UN on various resolutions
concerning Palestine and so on so forth,
whatever Palestine is, India typically
either abstains or votes against Israel.
Okay? So Israel, you could say from
their perspective, they have the right
to feel agrieved about that. H and then
what Israel does is that they put out
the wrong map of India according to
Indians. According to Indians, it's the
wrong map of India. According to the
world, it's the right map of right map
because um right maybe not. But you
know, some territories are currently
occupied by Pakistan and by China. But
we want to show those territories as
part of our uh our map. But the facts on
the ground says something else, right?
So that's why from Israel's perspective,
it may be right. But when Israel de
displays Arunachal Pradesh as part of
China, that is that borders on malicious
now. Right?
And you also have to ask yourselves, my
dear Indians, if Israel keeps saying
that they are against terrorism, why
have they never taken any action against
Pakistan? If they are worried about a
terrorist nation having nuclear weapons,
which is what they say about Iran, why
have they done nothing about Pakistan
having nuclear weapons?
It is also being alleged that Pakistan
helped Israel in the current
decapitation strike against Iranian
generals because a few weeks ago
apparently a few days or weeks ago
Pakistan what aim that fellow he gave a
a watch as a gift to Mr. Beri of Iran
and that watch perhaps carried some kind
of tracking device which allowed the
Israelis to take him out.
You see the so Pakistan and Israel looks
like there's a possibility that they may
be working together. So Indians are are
I just don't understand how naive
Indians can be including some very
prominent uh military experts and all
but uh yeah I I hope Indians can see
this and think without think beyond your
brainwashing.
I have nothing against Israel by the
way. Okay. I have nothing personal
against Israel. I would anytime take
Israel over over Palestine and all that.
No question about it.
If you ask me to choose between
supporting Palestine and supporting
Israel, I will always take Israel.
But if you ask me to to to choose
between Israel and Iran,
I would say I'm out of this matter. This
this doesn't concern me. I'm neutral.
And if you say that I have to choose
between um Isra between Iran continuing
to exist in its current shape and form
or a regime change in in Iran, I would
say I would prefer the regime of the
moolas to stay in place.
Yeah, the world is complicated.
Um Merin says mysterious support of
Indians to Israel is very sad. I would
say Indians should look at their
national interest first. We should have
nothing against Israel or Iran or
anybody, right? But this this
what Indians imagine that Israel is
India's best friend and we should
support them unconditionally. Well, that
is completely naive and and
ridiculous.
Vicki Sharma says, "Thank you for
building my confidence." Okay. I'm 23,
run an 8 figureure business.
Outstanding, sir. Outstanding. I like
that. pay 30% tax yet face bribery in
basic government work. UAE pays 0% t
tax. I love my country but feel stuck.
Would value your advice.
Go to the UAE. My advice to you is go to
the UAE.
Okay. Turn that 8 figure business into
10ig business. Then if you have some
extra money that you would like to use
to to
um help the country you love your
country then you can do it on a case by
case basis. I would say go to the UAE.
If this country is is you know not
treating you well it's not the country
that's not treating you well. It is the
system that is victimizing you. You see
Indians need to understand the country
doesn't victimize anybody. Our
civilization is not victimizing anybody.
It is this current colonial system which
hasn't changed from the British days
that is victimizing people. So if you
are being victimized and if you are if
you're being treated like this, if you
are being made to forced to pay bribes
otherwise nothing works, you know what?
Take your business elsewhere.
My my advice to you is move to the UAE.
Turn your 8 figureure business into a
10-figure business. then you can maybe
contribute something to India
in a way that doesn't force you to pay
any bribes. That's what I would say. But
I'm I'm so happy to see that you're
doing an 8 figure business. I would like
to see you do far better. So all the
best, you know, uh don't ever do
something that clips your wings. Always
try and u uh reach the fullest extent of
your potential wherever you have to go
for it.
Nikki Kizor says why Israel never shows
correct map of India? Well, that's
something Israel has to answer, right?
Why does Israel never say a thing
against Pakistan? Why do they never take
any action against Pakistan? They keep
on saying that we hate terrorism and is
and Iran is a terrorist nation. Hey,
what about Pakistan? Iran is nothing
compared to Pakistan. Israel does not
have any problem with terrorism. They
have a problem only with Iran.
Otherwise, they would do something
against Pakistan but they don't.
Uh Kaizen says the current government
does not seem to be pro- Hindu
civilization. It seems like they have
accept accepted the system secular and
socialist as it is and they're not
bringing any key reforms that will truly
unleash Bat's potential. My opinion my
opinion is that the government is
focusing on development on growth on
infrastructure etc etc. But if in by by
2050 India is no longer Indian then who
are you creating all this infrastructure
for? You're going to hand it over to to
the descendants of the Bangladesh work
who were living in India, right? Then
what's the point of all this
development? Something has to be done.
The first thing is very simple. Get rid
of all the foreign infiltrators.
Whatever the number is, it's somewhere
between 50 and 100 100 million.
Get rid of them. Whatever it takes to do
that. And secondly, yes, it's time that
we start building up our our
civilization again.
It starts the education system. Start by
teaching kids their their culture and
civilization and so on. So all of that
is not being done and which is very
unfortunate. It's it's yeah it's it's I
find it's very unfortunate.
That's my opinion.
Prudi sir thank you
really now says people like you are MSM
for me poor UPSC aspirants Hindu
mainstream media. Well thank you so
much. I think what you're trying to say
is that you said trying to say something
good. Uh
yeah, if if you if you're gaining some
kind of value from whatever I'm doing,
then I'm I'm glad. Okay, so these Q&A
sessions are more like u
it's you will get I'm I'm sure you will
gain more value from from other things
that I'm doing like the geostrategy
series, the Indian interest series and
all understanding America if that's
something that you're into. And I hope
that these Q&A also kind of throw light
on various things and how to think
differently etc. And if it's helping you
then I'm very glad about it. So yeah
thank you.
Dj Kamat says then do you think that
dharma needs a strong top- down
structure and centralized leadership to
secure its interests? Hinduism has
always been bottom up. Hinduism has
always been a super diverse civilization
super bottom up.
But the moment state support disappears
Hinduism disintegrates.
Hinduism has always thrived
historically. Please look back at
history. the past several thousand years
years of history. Hinduism is fragile.
Hinduism needs state support. Hinduism
thrives only when there is proper state
support from the top without
interference at the bottom.
Right? So how did Hinduism thrive in the
past? Hindu dharma all kinds of dharma,
Hindu dharma, jane dharma, bodha dharma
etc. Dharma, dharma, dharma, all these
different schools of thought. How did
they thrive? They thrived when the kings
and emperors would give grants to
temples to visha vidyales to
universities
they would give ongoing continuing
support to these institutions so that
they would not have to look for money.
They would get the money they need so
that they could just do their thing.
Teachers would just teach without having
to worry about fees. Which means that in
India education was free.
Temples were not just places of worship.
They were centers of education and so on
so forth. When it comes to various
manifestations of Indian culture, Indian
dance forms, Indian music, all of that
also had state patronage and support.
When it comes to science, mathematics,
astronomy, all that, you had state
support.
Who was the patron of the great
astronomer in mathematician Brahma
Gupta? Look it up. You all of these
great people had state support and state
patronage and that is what contributed
to the flourishing of dharma and to the
e fllororesence of Indian culture and
civilization.
That way Hinduism has always been bottom
up because all these geniuses come from
the bottom. But without top- down state
support, it all disintegrates.
I mean look at what happened after 1947.
Until 1947, all the so-called princely
states used to support culture. Now you
kill off the princely states and then
you have one central institution
somewhere that decides what grant to
give to which artist and not based on
the artists merit but allegedly they
will just give support to whoever is
going to will going to pay them bribes.
So that destroys culture.
So Hinduis so dharma needs a strong
top-down support structure
always does. It doesn't have to be
centralized in Delhi. It can be
centralized anywhere. It can be
centralized at the district level, state
level, whatever. But you need top down
support and then you can see bottom up
resurgence. That's how it works.
Um
ADL says, why did Israel aid India in 71
despite US ties? Because Israel is more
powerful than the US. It looks like
Israel can do whatever it likes. Israel
can take down an American warship and
smash it to bits and nothing happens.
Israel is a special nation. The the
Israeli people are chosen are the chosen
people of God, right? God's chosen
people. They can do whatever they like.
That's what it looks like. I'm just
saying based on the evidence, historical
evidence at our disposal.
Uh
okay. Uh Nachiket says, "Please discuss
the terrible cost ratio of US NATO." I'm
not sure what you mean by that. Cost
cause ratio of US versus NATO.
Cost versus cause. What's cost versus
cause? I am not sure what I'm not sure
what you mean, sir.
Cost versus cause. Sorry, I didn't get
it. Very sorry. Kumar Kanishka says,
"Why do we no longer have great movies
like Godfather, Shaw Shank Redemption,
Full Metal, Jacket, etc.? Why the
quality of cine cinema globally has gone
down overall?" I I I feel you, brother.
I feel you. I love movies.
If if if I had the opportunity, I would
go and watch two movies a week on the
big screen happily.
But we no longer have great movies. I
would love to I would love to pay my
money to a good cinema and watch two
movies a week as long as you have great
movies. But the movies today are are
it's mental torture to watch them. Utter
torture. I don't know what's happened.
They used to have such great movies back
in the past. Every week you would have
at least one good movie that you could
be able to watch. You can't. What's
happened? It's because of ideology
creeping into into uh the movie studios.
Now movies feel like lectures.
The the the objective of making a movie
is to lecture the the viewer.
That's I'm talking about Hollywood here.
Okay? Even Bollywood has become utter
trash. At least there used to be some
kind of quality in the past like 20 25
years ago. Today Bollywood movies are
just trash formulaic garbage, right? Uh
so what's happened in in Hollywood is
that movies are now left liberal
lectures. That's what they are. It's all
about lecturing the viewers as to how
they should think and how they should
behave and what is right and what is
wrong. And movies are so unrealistic
today. You have female superheroes who
can beat up a guy who is twice their
size. I mean, are you kidding me? Who's
going to believe that in real life? And
people, some people actually end up
believing this and then they think they
can do that. Uh, so the quality of
cinema has gone down. The last, what was
the last few good movies we've watched?
I think the Lord of the Rings in
Hollywood was good and uh maybe the
initial few James Bond movie the initial
first James Bond movie of of um the the
guy who retired recently Craig Craig
Craig whatever his name is Casino Royale
was okay and so on. Uh recently a couple
of
Tom Cruz movies were good. The latest um
the latest what was it? Uh, Mission
Impossible was fine and Top Gun was okay
and so on. Top Top Gun was surprisingly
not bad, etc. But overall, most movies
are just trash. There's no point
watching them. It's it's because of the
injection of ideology and and leftist
ideals, etc. into into what should be
just art, you know, when nobody wants to
pay money to be lectured. So,
Vive Singh says, "Israel allegedly
attacked Iran nuclear and military
installations, but Iran attacked
civilian areas of Israel. Do you
consider this to be a blunder or is it
will give Israel an excuse to escalate?
Uh, I'm going to stay out of this
matter. I'm going to stay out of the
matter." Uh, some people are saying that
is that Iran has attacked the center of
Tel Aviv. Some people are are giving a
counterargument. Not me. Not me. Some
other people are giving counter
arguments that you know Israel that Iran
is trying to hit military installations
in the middle of Tel Aiv because we can
see uh rockets going into the sky from
from residential areas.
Um then there's a counter argument that
these are defensive installations and so
on so forth. So it's an ongoing thing.
When there's war, there's war. Things
happen whichever way. Like like recently
the three-day war between India and
Pakistan. We hit Pakistani terrorist
infrastructure. We hit Pakistani
military infrastructure. The Pakistanis
were shelling Indian civilians.
So it's not a good thing to do. But uh
whatever. I think it's possible that
Israel may or may not I don't know. They
may or may not have military
installations in civilian areas. It's
possible. May or may not be possible.
I don't know. I'm not aware of what what
the deal is. So I think it's all a
battle of perception and narratives. My
point is this is not my fight. This is
not India's fight. We're going to stay
out of it and I hope that both sides
will calm down and and stop the stop the
war. But yeah, it's easier said than
done. Manikandan Wen Raman says can you
comment on TM
Tamil Nadu CM claims on sir? Look, I
don't get into Indian politics. I'm
sorry but I don't get into Indian
politics. Saraswati civilization being
mythical claims that killer is the
oldest important to refute such claims.
Civilizational continuity.
Okay, let me just say look the Saraswati
civilization. Saraspati Hindu
civilization we know there is culture
there is clear and ambiguous
archaeological evidence of cultural
continuity that goes back at least now
12,000 years.
Um so we have the earliest
archaeological site which was Birhana in
Hana which is about 9 and a half
thousand years old. We know that it's
carbon dated and that shows clear
evidence of cultural continuity
archaeological evidence of that you know
and then now they have found some some
place in Kutch or something which is
about 12,000 years old. I'm telling you
this is still just the beginning. More
than 2,000 archaeological sites exist on
the dry riverbed of the Saraspati which
have never been excavated. The moment
you start excavating those, it's going
to go back further and further and
further and further. Now I don't know
about Kil etc. There's always some
complaint coming out of Tamil Nadu that
Ked is not getting excavated. Well, why
doesn't the Tamil Nadu government do it?
No one stopping you, right? So my point
is this is all politics. I don't want to
get into this political matters. Okay.
Um what is absolutely clear my friends
is that the Saraspati Synindu region and
the the the civilizational u
infrastructure in this region goes back
tens of thousands of years at least
12,000 years now and if you look at the
Gulf of Kat archaeological complex which
is underwater under the ocean it was
last above the ocean about 10 11 12,000
years ago and it's not some some piece
of rock or thing. It's a complex of
cities, a network of cities. And the
cities are laid out in a grid structure
like Manhattan
10, 11, 12,000 years ago. And they are
laid out just like the other cities in
the Sarasota Hindu region, but they are
older. So my point is we need to stop
all this stupid idiotic infighting
whoever may be doing it. Okay? We are
all one civilization, one culture.
North, south, east, west, doesn't
matter. We are one. One culture, one
civilization. We all have the same
genetics also despite the skin color or
whatever. Yeah. So that's what I would
say about this. We need to stop
fighting.
Din Dor says, "I have seen several
images of public servants not following
traffic rules. Should I start uploading
them anonymously on Telegram?" Sir, it's
entirely up to you. It's up to you, sir.
I don't know. I don't know. I'm sure it
happens. I'm sure it happens. I I would
leave this this this decision to you,
sir.
Bipol Singh says you vehemently wanted
the Indian forces in PK during operation
Synindor. Then change your stance. You
weren't privy to info. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
I am a ch stance changer, right? That's
what you're saying. Huh? I still say I
wanted this to happen. When did I change
my stance? What are you talking about?
I changed my stance today saying I
wasn't privy to info the government. I I
that is not a change of stance. I still
am not privy to info the government.
What are you talking about?
Can't neu say the same thing about
bullish etc. Okay whatever
sahil says can should India become an
autoarchy should yeah but can can we
for that we need to find oil reserves we
need to find mineral reserves everything
that that is enough to sustain ourselves
for for 100 plus years.
So Russia is an otaki because it is so
large, such an enormous geographical
region that they have everything they
need. They have oil, gas, coal, uh iron,
ore, copper, ore, every single mineral
resource that they may or may not need.
They have all the chemical resources
they need for fertilizers. They have
enough agricultural land. They have
everything they need. In India, it's not
the case. There are, for example, we
don't have sufficient oil and gas thus
far. I think we may have reserves but we
have not looked for them. Similarly,
there are other things that we may not
have. For example, rare rare earths. Of
course, once again, we have not looked
for them. We have been sleeping.
So, India should strive to become an
utarchy for sure. No question about
that.
Um, will we be able to do that? I think
we we do have a very large land mass. No
question about it. So, I'm sure it's
possible if we try hard enough. Vinay
Jooshi says what happened to Totsis in
Rwanda? Who fueled what fueled it? There
was a civil war kind of situation in
Rwanda in I think in '94 or something
about 21 years ago. Um Hutus versus
Totsis and this was fueled by the
Catholic Church and the Catholic Church
actually eventually apologized for this.
Right? So the Catholic Church caused a
genocide in Rwanda.
The Rwanda genocide. Can you believe it?
Veian prince says okay thank you sir
please consider a history this is a
history question rather than a religious
one are the Syrian Christians of Kerala
good example of indigenous Christians
meaning they're still culturally Indian
and Hindu I am not aware of this I don't
know about the the lifestyle and
etc and so on so forth of the Syrian
Christians of Kerala I don't know um
they they seem to claim that they are
very culturally Indian and Hindu they
still follow certain Hindu practices
while also worshiping Jesus Christ and
so on. Um, so if that is true, if if if
what I've if the claims I've heard are
true, then it means that they are a good
example of indigenous people who have
adopted a foreign religion but who still
hold on to some indigenous cult customs
and all that which I'm sure that the
Catholic Church will not like very much
if they come to know about this because
in the past they used to burn people for
that.
But yeah, I mean it's possible, but I'm
not aware personally.
I I this is not not something that
interests me very much. The lifestyle of
indigenous converts to other religions
and so on. It's never been something
that has been part of what I've you know
researched. So I can't really say this
is not part of my sphere of knowledge
unfortunately.
Vishal Ro says every control country is
alone except for Israel. Maybe that's
true. with Israel you have the US and
all other US faciles maybe even
Pakistan. So
okay Barati Baratia says okay uh grand
Sarasati river 18,000 years before
pleasant present that I claimed in
episode 258 comes comes from a 2814
report by government remote sensing
energy agency ISRO clearly describing
various no no question about it no
question about it the Saraspati river
would go back more than 18,000 years uh
as old as 40,000 years years before
present and other rivers used to flow
into this great river and And there were
changes of course and all that. Yeah.
No, no question about it. That's not the
point. There's no question. This river
was very ancient tens of thousands of
years years old and it dried out only
about around 1500 BC. And it still
exists to some extent in North India.
It's called the Gagar Gagar Hakar River.
Every every year during the rainy
season, it again flows and overflows and
becomes the mother of floods. So it
still exists up north in northern India.
Hana that region. So there's no question
that what you have said is correct. But
you had tied with that with the age of
the riga.
So if the Saraswati is let's say 40,000
years old, does it mean the Rigida is
also 40,000 years old? That I would not
agree necessarily.
It can perhaps mean that the rigida was
written when the Sarasati was first
born, but it necessarily doesn't mean
that.
So one has to when one makes claims
based on scientific evidence one has to
be as rigorous as possible and as
skeptical as possible and be as
conservative as pos as possible
otherwise people will say you're a
charlatan and you are a conspiracy
theorist.
So
because the riged does me mention the
Saraspati as a rear that is a river
that's clearly in her prime a loudly
roaring river the mother of floods and
so on and so forth and so on and so
forth the kind of description that you
have is that of a grand glorious rather
majestic and scary river right so it
means that the rigida the authors of the
Riga who wrote these lines
they saw saw the river in her prime not
they did not see a river in her decline
which means that was written closer to
6,000 BC
of course it's possible it was written
at 18,000 BC but there's no evidence of
that but at least we can say it was
closer to 6,000 BC then to 1500 BC so
that's what I'm saying it's a nuanced
argument
uh hopefully you understand
why Gaming YT says does planet X exist
well if it exists and if we have
evidence of it will be all over the news
so we haven't found yet planet X, planet
9, 9, whatever. So why do we believe
something may exist? It's because of the
because of the chaotic and elongated
orbits of the the solar system objects
that exist beyond the orbit of Neptune.
Those are not in line with the plane of
the solar system. The solar system
planets are all in one plane. It's
because the very early solar system
before any planets formed, it was just a
protostellar disc which was spinning
around the center like a frisbee. So it
was all in one plane flat. So all the
planets that exist today are in that the
original plane of the protostellar disc.
But there are some objects beyond the
orbit of Neptune that are inclined or
they have inclined orbits at at sharp
angles to the plane of the solar system.
So something has disrupted the orbits of
these objects. So that tells us
something is there out there which we we
perhaps can't see and that's why people
are looking for this planet. Maybe
there's a big planet out there that's
too far away for us to see. Maybe it's
out there in darkness and we are not
able to see it but maybe we can detect
it using various methodologies. So
that's the deal but we haven't found it
yet.
Okay. Geopolitical Dub says how do I
deal with the Indian education system?
You have to put up with it. You have to
get your degrees and get out of it and
don't allow it to corrupt your mind.
So I everybody goes through this. At
least I was aware that this was all
nonsense. I remember when I was in I
don't know what standard 8th or 9th
standard I I had this history book in
which they they said that there was this
poet called Ferdosi who wrote a
biography of Shah Jahan called the
Shahame.
That's what my textbook told me. Now I
went back and did some research and I
discovered that Ferdosi was an Iranian
Persian poet who wrote the Shaame is the
chronicle of all the Persian kings
starting from the rigidic age.
It has nothing to do with Shajahan but
this this Indian textbook was teaching
me that Fossi wrote this as a biography
of Shajahan that the Turk ruler will
rule over India. So you have to first
recognize the fact if you're a student
that the Indian education system is full
of garbage and full of lies.
So you have to pass exams and get good
marks. So just temporarily memorize this
garbage. Write it down in your exams and
immediately forget it. And if you want
to really learn about the world, do some
extracurricular learning. That's
reading. That's what I would say. That's
how you deal with the education system.
Don't allow it to brainwash you. Don't
allow it to to to subvert your mind
ideologically. Okay? Always be aware
that this is an attempt to subvert my
mind. So that's what I would say. So the
earlier you deal with it and get rid of
it the better it is.
Kajoro bithorn says is red note CN
Instagram not banned in India part of
influence operation you spoke of very
anti-India but some warm
people-to-people ties to a Chinese okay
Chinese girl in exchange program in
Delhi made nice daily vlogs interesting
okay red note is some kind of Chinese
app is it I'm not aware of it a Chinese
version of Instagram if it's a Chinese
app it's part of the influence
operations okay yeah so I'm glad you put
this out what is red note let's let's
Google it shall we let us google it
together What is a red note?
Um,
Rednote.
What is Red Note? It's It's a Xiao Xiao
Hongu Chinese social media and
e-commerce platform. It's a combination
of Instagram, Tik Tok, and Pinterest and
beauty, fashion, travel, blah blah blah
blah blah blah blah. This is what it
looks like. Is it available in India? I
thought the the government of India had
banned a whole lot of Chinese apps. It's
still available in India. If it is then
it's definitely guaranteed 100% path of
the Chinese influence operations
100% guaranteed and of course you will
have some nice Chinese girls who will be
in exchange programs in Delhi who will
make nice daily vlogs saying nice things
about India so you'll balance things out
80% it will be anti-India but 20% people
saying nice things about India so
Indians feel no it's not all biased see
because Indians are so stupid they will
see one good thing and they'll say oh no
no no no you see there's this example
over here So it's to fool Indians. You
see most Indians are such incredibly
gullible people that because on this app
most people are anti-India but there are
like two three Chinese girls who are
saying nice things about India. So
they'll say no no no all Chinese people
are not bad. See we have to we have to
see this these people also they are
saying nice things about India. So
that's how we do the the the the
influence operations right. So yeah, I'm
sure it is part of these influence ops
that you are that that I had mentioned
that I had referred to. Feminist slayer
says is it false? First, if the velocity
of a body is zero, then the acceleration
can be non zero. Secondly, a body may
moving at con constant velocity can have
acceleration.
Okay, velocity is dx by dt. It's a
vector quantity. Okay, it will have a
direction. It's also part of vector
space. So velocity is dx by dt. X is the
the the change X is the distance. X is
your your it's your X coordinate, right?
And dx by dt is your change in the x
coordinate with respect to time. So it's
the motion.
So velocity is dx by dt. Acceleration is
d² x by dt squ which is the change in in
the rate of velocity. So if your
velocity is constant 0 is a constant
then if you if you differentiate that
with respect to time it's going to be
zero which means acceleration will be
zero. So if your velocity is zero or if
it's constant then acceleration is going
to be zero
right. So both of your questions are the
same question actually that if the
velocity of of a body is constant
whether it is 2 or 28 or zero all these
are constants then can the acceleration
be non zero it can't the acceleration
will be zero because it's simple
differentiation with respect to time and
that's going to give you zero if you
differentiate a constant with respect to
time it's going to give you zero so
acceleration will be zero it cannot have
a non-zero acceleration
all right
says I sent you an email on research
collaboration sometimes some days back
waiting a response. I love to check
I have a couple of email ids that I use
for official purposes and I have people
screen that for me and they send me what
they think I I need to look into and I
have given them instructions as to what
I need to look into.
Uh so I don't have the time to go
through all the emails because that will
become very tedious and very
timeconuming because I'll get so many
emails. So I've given very clear
instructions as to what are the kind of
emails that need to be brought to my
attention. So uh okay I'll I'll look
into few days back if you had told me
which date it was that you sent me it
would have made my life so much easier.
A few days back mean can mean 3 days or
30 days. I don't know what it means. I
I'll try and look into it personally.
Research collaboration. Okay.
Okay. Sharma says thoughts on the rise
of Christianity in the west among young
people particularly young men. We are
feeling disenfranchised by school and
media. Women are pushed to the left
while men are demonized. Yes. Yes.
That's what h what's what's going on in
the west. It's also what's happening in
India. So as as a response
people want to fall back to some
traditional values and all that. And in
the west that has usually meant
Christianity in the past thousand or so
years. Some people especially in the
Nordic countries are going back even
further and they are trying to do this
Nordic pagan revival Assatru etc. But in
most parts of Europe it's going to be
people going back trying to go back to
Christianity. So it's just a natural
knee-jerk response to the demonization
of men of the destruction of culture and
of the imposition of of of
non-culture on society. Uh it's it's a
response to the imposition of ugliness
on society. If you look at art today,
art is ugliness today. The modern art,
it's just ugly garbage. Any any any
idiot can can produce that.
Historically, art used to be very
difficult to produce and that's why it
was so much in demand and that's why it
was so valuable. So there's going to be
some push back to to all of this that's
happening. And in the west, yeah, people
will want to go back to the only
recourse they have, which is
Christianity, right? because nobody
knows what pagan religion was like and
Christianity demon demonized that for a
thousand years. So people will want to
fall back on the on on the old culture
which is Christianity which is a kind of
a logical response to what is being done
because people can sense that some
forces are trying to re-engineer
society.
Some people are trying to re-engineer
the way we live our lives. They're
trying to destroy the fabric of society
by alienating men and women from each
other and so on by by demonizing men and
putting women on a pedestal and making
women you know veer to the left and
making men feel r feel feel uh lost
wherever they are and so on. Men are
demonized. Yeah. Because of all of these
things, you're going to have the rise of
Christianity and whatever traditional
cultures exist among young people,
especially young men, I would suggest
suppose. And there's al also this this
rise of nostalgia for the Roman Empire
and so on so forth. So yeah, yeah, this
is all a natural response to what is
being done to people
and society. ICBM says why don't we talk
about India, India, Indonesia enough?
Surely enhancing naval economic
cooperation will help secure the
IndoPacific encounter China's expansion.
I don't know why we don't speak about
India and Indonesia enough. Let's put
some put uh this on the on the screen
for some context. I have been trying to
uh you know talk about Indonesia to
bring people's notice to Indonesia. the
fact that Indonesia is a neighboring
country of India. When you ask Indian
students which are India's neighboring
countries the first country they will
say is Pakistan
then they will say whatever other
nations most people don't know that
Burma is a neighboring country and
nobody will name Indonesia as a
neighboring country. Let me show you
something. What is the distance between
India and Indonesia? Okay, let's let's
try and say the distance between India
and Indonesia.
It's about one less than 175 kilometers.
Indonesia is less than 175 kilometers
from India. Okay. And when it comes to
Thailand for example, if you want to see
the distance between India and Thailand,
that again is about less than 500
kilometers.
Okay, that may be of course that may be
Myanmar. But if you see this Fuket for
example,
this region, it's about 500 kilometers.
So even even Thailand is a neighboring
country but nobody's aware of it.
Thailand Indonesia are both neighboring
countries. These are important
countries. These are historically
civilizationally being part of our
sphere of sphere sphere of influence. If
you go to Indonesia, people look like
us.
It's Indonesia. It's not Sonia, right?
And the greatest period in Indonesian
history was the Majapahit Empire which
was a Hindu empire. But we are not
taught these things. There are no
people-to-people connections. The
Indians who go to Indonesia act like
idiots. They have alienated the people
of Bali because of their stupid
behavior. The Indian tourists who go
there and so on. But the deal is that
India and Indonesia are natural
partners. Right? We would it would be it
would be great to enhance uh economic
ties between India and Indonesia. It
would be great to enhance naval ties
between India and Indonesia. It would be
great if we can if we can maybe supply
arms and ammunition and so on to
Indonesia. It would be great. So I think
Indonesia it's it's a natural partner
for India civilizational partner even
though Indonesia is you you could say
it's a Muslim country today but the
Indonesian Muslims have not given up
their culture they still have
they still have Sanskrit names they have
the weirdest name combinations
Muhammad Vishnu I mean that's the kind
of names they have meawati sukarnutri is
a pure Sanskrit name but imagine
Muhammad Vishnu
[Laughter]
It's it's a name that will offend two
religion at the same time
but yeah my point is they still are
holding on to their culture okay which
is Indian culture and it was never
imposed on Indonesia by force never ever
and so on so it would be Indonesia is a
great long-term partner for India
civilizational partner maybe ge
geopolitical partner as well We should
enhance all kinds of cooperation with
Indonesia. Wonderful country. Wonderful
country.
Okay. Vidi says spiritual leaders of
power. Yes. Yet why can't they take
initiative to remove foreign education?
Isn't it their responsibility? If
government has failed, sases have
protected bat before.
Um
not sure how how it how it works and
what they can do. uh some spiritual
leaders are very powerful of course in
India. Uh one can think of a few. Uh can
they start their own educational board
and so on?
I suppose they could. Maybe it's too
much of a task. I I don't know. I don't
So maybe they can, maybe they should. I
would say you're right. It's an
interesting point you're raising. um at
least look they can't possibly remove
foreign education from India but they
can set up a parallel system of
education that would be better for India
civilizationally and culturally that's
something they could do maybe they are
taking some initiatives at some level
you know v the shalas or whatever but
maybe it needs to be done more
aggressively and it needs to be it needs
to be pushed more outwards that sort of
thing perhaps
um yeah so maybe maybe it's something
they they can do better possibly. Yeah,
it's a good point you're raising, Vidi.
Good point.
MK says, "Why Israel sold weapons to
India during cargle war despite being US
number one ally? Didn't US intelligence
not find and pressurize Israel?" The US
cannot pressurize Israel. Israel is not
America's number one ally.
Israel is not America's number one ally.
America is Israel's number one ally.
It's the other way around.
Okay? So, the US doesn't get to
pressurize Israel. No, the US dare not
pressurize Israel.
The Israel does whatever it wants. It's
it's Israel that pressurizes the US.
That's how it works.
Okay. Ralph Rupchik says, "Nations like
the US, EU nations, UK and Ireland are
hit by a recession in information
technology. Why us Indians think there
are way better opportunities in it than
here? Why were we never hit severely by
rep recession in it?
Why do Indians think there are better
opportunities in information technology
outside of India than here?
It's not like that. The living standards
are better outside of India. The
salaries are better outside of India. It
has nothing to do about uh better
opportunities in IT. Whatever
opportunities in it exist in the US, in
Ireland, in in whatever EU nations, in
UK, okay, those opportunities come with
way better salary and way better living
standards. That's why Indians want to
go, Indians want to escape the horrors
of India, the poverty, the even if you
are getting a good salary, you have
horrible abysmal living standards. It
takes you two hours to travel one way to
office and two two hours to come back to
your home. Four hours in a day are gone
there. Who wants to live in India if if
this is what you get for all the money
that you are paying as a salary as as
tax to the government? That's why
Indians want to leave the country. Do
you understand? It has nothing to do
with whether this a recession or not.
And I don't know about whether we have
been hit severely by recessions in IT or
not. But AI is coming. AI is going to
wipe the IT industry clean. Okay.
Programming is already to a large
extent. You don't need programmers now.
If you understand programming and if you
have some experience as as a program as
a as a project manager then you can have
I you can have AI do everything for you.
So that is coming now and that's going
to wipe the entire field of IT clean
very soon.
Messi AI IM says what do you think is
the reason for the Air India crash?
Look, I don't know. It looks like from
my perspective I could be wrong. It
looks like there was a simultaneous dual
engine failure. That's what it looks
like.
because the plane is taking off and
suddenly it just loses lift, loses power
and just go just goes down. Looks like
both engines failed at the same time. I
mean I cannot see any other reason.
Um it that's what it looks like to me.
Of course I am not an expert and we'll
have to wait for the official report to
come. It's a big mystery and it's very
strange. So I think it's too early for
me to give any answer. My hunch from
whatever little I understand is is that
it looks like u dual engine failure
simultaneous.
Ruchita and Ritik say thank you. Well,
thank you so much for the kind words.
Thank you so much.
Swastik G. Thank you very much. Thank
you. Dr. Ritik Patnak says so many
YouTubers celebrating Israel's attack on
Iran. Well,
telling that Isra that Iran is
Pakistan's ally. What? What? Iran is
Pakistan's ally.
Okay. Israel is our ally. What alliance
treaty do we have with Israel? Who are
these people?
Who are these people? Making it
oversimplified. Only you can give. Well,
thank you, sir. Thank you. Thank you,
Dr. Patnak. I it just I mean the the
level of of analysis that we have in
India today, it it it's it it's painful
to see it. It hurts your brain to see
the kind of analysis that passes for the
kind of garbage that passes for
analysis.
Why does India have to celebrate
Israel's attack on Iran?
How is Iran Pakistan's ally? What utter
nonsense? Iran launched missile strikes
on Pakistan not too long ago. Iran
accused Pakistan of of doing terrorism
in Iran. How is Iran Pakistan's ally?
Who are these people?
Israel puts out wrong maps of India on a
consistent basis. It's a pattern. But
Israel is our ally. And it's not just
about Kashmir. It's about Arunachal
Pradesh. They are portraying Arunachal
Pradesh as part of China. Even though
Arunachal Pradesh, we have facts on the
ground. It is within India. We have
Indian flags all over the place. We have
the Indian government, India, Indian
army everywhere. And yet Israel is
portraying Arunachal Pradesh as part of
China. And these people are claiming
Israel is our ally
and so on. And I I remember some
recently some some big Indian YouTuber
analyst
calling the Isra calling the Iran
foreign minister a very bad bad word. I
mean what kind of people are these? They
have no idea what the Indian national
interest is. So anyway okay well thank
you for bringing this to our notice. Dr.
Patnak MK says do our diplomats know
about actual geopolitical picture like
you for example many nations are US
forals? I'm pretty sure they know. Come
on. Come on. I'm pretty sure they know.
I'm sure they know better than me. Okay,
let's not let's not put it that way. I'm
sure they know better than me. I'm sure
they know things that I know I don't
know about. Okay, they are diplomats and
they are with the government of India.
They will know better than someone like
me.
Zemo says your road map road map to
geopolitics from scratch.
You have to start with learning history.
Start with reading a lot of history. It
will take you years to do that. Only
then will the geopolitical connections
the the the the causal chain become
apparent to you cause and effect that
when something like this happens what
are the possible outcomes or if
something like this has happened what
could be the cause for that. This is
something you can only learn by by
studying history in great detail. Not
just Indian history but history from all
across the world. That gives you way
more case studies. You to study military
campaigns. You to study Caesar's
campaigns Napoleon's campaigns. you to
study Alexander's campaigns. Um, you to
study the the the histories of the great
dynasties, whether it's the Egyptian
dynasties or the Persian dynasties, the
Mesopotamian dynasties, the Chinese
dynasties, Rome, all of that. You to
study the age of colonization, how
colonization happened, uh how various
continents were colonized. Um, you to
study the history of warfare. You to do
all of that. It takes a lot and a lot
and a lot of time. Uh only then can you
understand the cause causal chain. Then
you to then to read the great
geostrategists. You have to read
Mackander.
You have to read Claus Sevitz. You have
to read Switchin if you want. You have
to read people like Kissinger and
Brazinski. Well, that gives you a very
Makaveillan approach to life. You can
also read the Artasi. You can read
Sununzu. You can read Makaveli.
It it doesn't hurt to learn game theory,
right? Especially if you want to
understand how to do forecasting and all
that, forecasting with multiple
scenarios and assign probabilities and
all that. You have to study some game
theory properly mathematically. You it
helps to learn statistics
and so on. It's it's a pretty long
complicated road map. You can it's not
like you read two textbooks and you're
done with geopolitics. Now I know
geopolitics.
Doesn't work like that. Um yeah. So
that's how it goes. I'm just giving you
an very honest answer. It's a very long
road.
Uh Vun says, "Raising standards every
day. Thank you for it." Well, thank you
so much for your comment and your
contribution, sir.
Gro says, "Asimali
news jut
such
that he went to the US. He has not gone
to the US. Has he been invited? We'll
see about that. We'll see about that.
Doesn't matter. Doesn't matter.
[Laughter]
Nachiket Jaman says I meant bad cost
versus cause ratio
of western military operations. Cost
versus cause. What is cost versus cause?
I can understand return on investment. I
can understand
cause versus effect ratio or cost versus
effect ratio ratio. What is cost versus
cause? Let me try and maybe maybe I'm
really stupid. Okay, maybe I don't
understand. Let me let me just Google it
if if I'm making some stupid mistake
here. Cost cause ratio. Cost cause
ratio. What does it mean?
cost cause ratio.
I have never heard this term before.
It's not a standard or universally
recognized financial term or any term.
I can understand cost to income ratio,
cost to revenue ratio. I know cost
benefit ratio and so on. What is cost to
cause ratio? See,
look, I'm not trying to make fun of you
at all. I have never heard this term
before. That's why I'm confused.
bad cost versus cause ratio. I don't
know what that means, sir.
I'm I'm really sorry.
I don't know. I don't know what it
means.
Kumar Kanish says South Africa finally
beat Australia in the world world test
championship final, winning an ICC
trophy for the first time ever, I
suppose. Right. Well, good for them.
Good for them. They finally have
succeeded in not choking. Well, good for
South Africa. good for them. I've seen
them lose so many finals and all that or
semi so many semi-finals. I remember
when I was a kid.
I watched the one of the semi-finals of
the 1992 World Cup, England versus South
Africa. South Africa needed 22 runs from
I think it was 22 runs from seven balls
and then there was a 10-minute period of
rain and then the Duckworth Lewis system
came in the way and it said now it said
22 runs from one ball
and that's why they lost the semi-final.
And I've seen them lose so many of the
semi-finals. I saw Virindra Seag ball
the last over and he got closer out and
god knows who else out and we won that
match. And we recently won the T20
championship against South Africa. South
Africa was winning easily and then they
choked. So I'm glad to see South Africa
finally get something. I'm I'm glad to
see them defeat Australia, their old
enemy. It's been very hard for South
Africa to beat Australia. I believe uh
Aiden Marram came good. Good for you,
bro. A H Aiden. And I heard that Timba
Buma came good. Well, good for you,
Captain. So, overall happy. Good. Good
for them. They deserve it.
Uh Vive Singh says, "Except for Lava,
Indian mobile companies failed to
survive." Well, that's unfortunate. Did
they fail to survive? Uh does Lava still
exist? I remember there was something
called Microax which was just a a
Chinese brand with Indian Indian thing
on top but whatever. Yeah. Okay. If LA
is still surviving you see what we need
is innovation. What we need is our own
research and development and our own u
innovations in technology.
What Indians have done historically
in technology is that they just import
stuff from China and they put their own
um own brand on top of that. That's it.
That's terrible.
Okay. Navi Singh Nav Singh Baj says I'm
curious as to why there's no 4K CCTV
cameras in cockpit and cabin. I think
it's not the norm. There's no reason
except that it's not the norm. We don't
do it.
So in aircraft you have uh uh the the
flight recorders right the so-called
black box which is which is actually
bright orange and that um records
everything that happens in the aircraft.
It it uh records all the
all the events in the cabin. All the
sounds, all the voices that are, you
know, all the voice recordings of the
pilot, co-pilot, etc. talking to each
other, communicating with air traffic
control, communicating with
communicating with whoever else, all of
that is recorded. Plus all the
telemetry, etc. is recorded. All the all
the all the data of all the instruments
and flight controls and whatnot, all of
that is recorded. And that is all part
of the uh flight recorder which is
called the black box. Why is there no 4K
CCTV camera? Well, I've seen pilots
uh you know pilots are known to vlog
these days. There are these channels on
YouTube in which there are pilots with
the with typically pro or DJI cameras
and they record the outside of the
cockpit. So the camera is put in front
and you can see the nose of the plane
and you can see what's in front of the
plane. So pilots do that and I think
some airlines allow them to do that. But
why no 4K recording
CCTV recording of the of the cockpit and
cabin? Well, I don't know. It's never
been the norm and that's why nobody has
done it and because it's not the norm.
It just continues the way it is.
Uh Dhj Kamat says NU was anti-Indic or
victim of unknown circumstances. Nu Neu
G was nobody's victim sir. Nuji was so
great and so magnificent that he only
had victims if he did. He was nobody's
victim. He was too great to be a victim.
Anti-indic. How can you accuse somebody
as magnificent as Shin Aruji of being
anti-indic?
He was the pinnacle that we should
aspire to reach.
He of course did say you know that uh
Indian temples make him feel all
horrible and full of dread and so on. So
well he was so enlightened and so great
that this is how he felt about Indian
temples.
Quarty U123 says curious about
evolution. Curious how evolution
explains the origin of the first humans.
If they appear on different continents
how would they even have met?
See according to the theory of evolution
everything starts at one point. So
humans would not originate
simultaneously on different continents.
they would originate in one place and
from there they would spread to other
continents and there they would evolve
differently perhaps.
So it's like u it's it's like the the
theory of the origin of the the human
chimpanzeee divergence
right see see our closest relatives are
the chimpanzees which they share about
98 something% of our DNA so we are
almost the same and beyond the
chimpanzees the closest relatives for us
are the gorillas who also have about 96
96 or so percent of of our DNA so how
did humans and chimpan is diverge. So
there's a theory of the rift valley
origin that you know over time the rift
valley became wider and wider and the
the the groups of apes who lived on both
sides they became separated and they
evolved differently. So one became the
chimpanzees and whatever and one became
the humans and something similar must
have happened to the common ancestor of
the humans chimpanzes and gorillas and
somehow the gorillas split before the
human chimpanzeee split. So humans
originated out of this split between
humans and chimpanzees and they
originated in one place. That's the best
that we know about. Okay. So the best
theory is that we originated in Africa
and from there groups of humans traveled
to various continents.
So and and in some cases they they they
thrived in some in some cases they went
extinct. So we do have ancient humans
who have been found in Southeast Asia
more than a million years ago. They
existed but they they they died out. So
that experiment failed and the only
human species that still exists today is
us. So they did not appear on different
continents simultaneously. They
originated on in one place. The best
theory says that it that humans
originated in Africa and from Africa
they went to different continents
multiple times. Some of these migrations
failed and they died out and some some
succeeded. So the Neanderthal migration
which happened maybe 400,000 years
before today um or maybe 500,000 half a
million years before today it was a
migration of of humans ancient humans
out of Africa into uh the Israel region,
West Asia region and also into Europe
and perhaps I'm not sure about India but
certainly into those regions and then
you had homo sapiens going out of Africa
about 80,000 maybe years before today
and we met our Neanderthar cousins and
we acquired some the DNA through in
interbreeding but the neonals turned out
to be not as agile as us as us and they
died out they left some DNA in us and
today we are the only humans that
survive so yeah that's the complicated
back and forth scenario
proud Udya says 10 years ago I when I
travel states out of states people used
to say where is Odisha is it in west
Bengal no one knew about Odisha But
today Odisha is leading in iron boxside
steel with large strategic coastline.
What's my opinion? I I think Odisha is
one of the nicest states in the country.
I think the Odia people are some of the
nicest people in the whole of the
country.
Okay. Some it is said some states we
have people who are not so nice. Okay.
I'm not naming anybody but I think Odias
are the nicest people in the country.
very gentle, very civilized, very kind.
So, and maybe maybe I have some kind of
bias towards Orisa because I was born in
Odisha. Okay. But I think Odisha I am
not Odia but I was born in Odisha. So I
I think and
the last time I was in Odisha was when I
was 2 months old. After that I've not
been in Oisha. But I think Oisha is
wonderful. It's it's Odisha is Kolinga.
It's the ancient heartland of our
civilization. Before Partiputra became a
thing, Kolinga was the thing and the the
great people of Kolinga, they Indianized
the whole of Subarabumi in Southeast
Asia long before the Cholas went there.
It was the the people of Kolinga who who
slowly gradually brought Indian
civilization all across Surabi, all
across Southeast Asia. It was because of
Orisha this happened because
of of um you know the travels to to
Subagumi to to Vietnam to the kingdom
kingdom of Funan which was which was
founded by an Indian king and a a local
princess and so on that that Indian king
was was from Kolinga of course his name
was Condinia I think if I'm not mistaken
and so on. So I think Oisha has a
glorious history. I think the Bay of
Bengal should be called the sea of
Kolinga. Okay. And Oisha has tremendous
natural resources, tremendous natural
beauty and all. So I would love to see
Orisa prosper tremendously and I think
there's tremendous potential in Oisha.
Okay. Shihaji, thank you so much sir.
Thank you.
Shiva Rajput says, "What sources do you
follow for unbiased and accurate
geopolitical analysis? Also, what
sources can we rely on ourselves? Since
truth always lies in the gray areas, not
just the black and the white. I look at
the world from a 360 degree perspective.
I look at all sources. See, when I when
I do the analysis for my geostrategy
episodes in a week, I typically go
through more than 1,000
primary sources, pieces of news. And
these are not just Times of India or
such such stuff. I look at news from all
over the world. I look at the news
sources of our enemies which are
guaranteed to be biased against us. I
look at that. I look at Pakistani news
sources sometimes. I look at American
news sources. I look at UK based news
sources. I look at French news sources.
I will look at Japanese news sources. I
will look at Chinese news sources,
Russian news sources. I will look at a
sources from Africa. I will look at
financial news source. I look at
everything.
I will look at Al Jazzer.
I look at everything but I know what
bias each of these has because of my
experience. So I know what the truth
could be and once you look at a certain
developing developing story from all
these different perspectives at least
for me I know what really is happening.
That's how I do it. But I can do it
because I understand each of these
sources what their specific biases are.
Uh so what sources can you rely on
yourselves? Well, I would say look at
everything but be aware that everything
has some bias.
Okay? And the truth always lies
somewhere in between especially in the
in the present day geopolitical climate
because every news item is actually a
narrative.
The truth is not entirely there in the
news item. It the news item that you're
going to read is going to put forth a
certain perspective on what's happening.
It's not going to tell you what what
exactly is happening. is going to be
covered and and colored with some bias.
So you have to understand recognize that
and over time you can get a sense of
what what each uh news outlet's biases
are and then you can do a better job of
understanding what's really happening.
Uh Ragavan says I read a PCM genetic
study from 2009
showing Shia Muslims in Lacnau carry
haplo groups typically found in Greek
and Levantine populations. What happened
in the past? Well, unless I read the
study, I can't really tell you. But of
course, look, the history of human
beings is a history of migrations.
Um, so it's possible. Look, plenty of
Indians will have a little bit of this
and this, a little bit of that foreign
DNA. So what doesn't mean we're not
Indians. If you go to
you go to Turkey and look at their DNA,
how much of it is Turk DNA?
So look, people have always India has
always attracted immigrants.
India doesn't attract immigrants today
because India is just standing back on
its feet after 1,000 years of
colonization and foreign occupation. So
India is still in a state of devastation
whether you realize it or not. But
before the foreign occupation happened,
let's say in 800 AD, 900 AD, India was a
gloriously rich place.
And a place like that will always
attract foreign immigrants.
If you look back at various cemeteries
from the Harapan era, the so-called
Harapan era, you will find cemeteries
full of first generation immigrants who
came from somewhere else. And you can
tell that from from u from the analysis
of their bones, the kind of food and
water they they've ingested, it is
different from what the locals their
makeup their their bone makeup is like.
So India has always attracted people
from from outside. Okay. And if you look
at the skeletons of the Rup Kundal lake
where two disastrous event have hap
events have happened over almost 2,000
years. You will see a low large number
of people or pilgrims who would come
there were from somewhere in Europe in
the caucases region or something. So
it's always been like that. Lots of
foreigners. India has always attracted
lots of foreigners and maybe some of
them settled down over here and yeah so
the genetic gen genetic uh studies will
bring out these old histories that
people have forgotten right
suchin kandelwal says what's really
happening in China
with rumors again swirling that she is
being replaced China plus us to rearm
Pakistan again for re rematch on
operation sindur listen I don't pay
attention to rumors if something happens
we look into
Um I have not seen any of these rumors.
Every few months they start the rumor
that Xiinping is being replaced and
there's a coup in China and all that. I
remember 2023 there were again these
rumors of Xiinping being replaced and I
had put out a video saying that Ping is
not going anywhere when all the the the
Indian YouTubers the great YouTubers
were saying yes Xiinping a
so look let's not pay attention to
rumors if something happens we'll we'll
look into that. China, US to rearm
Pakistan again for rematch and
operation. They would love to do that.
The Chinese and the Americans see eye to
eye when it comes to Pakistan. Maybe
Israel also sees to sees eye to eye to
eye with them when it comes to Pakistan.
So they would like to rearm Pakistan and
maybe do a rematch operation Synindur in
the future. Mr. says Pakistan's nuclear
doctrine doesn't make sense to me. When
reading from their strategic
perspective, what's the real message
they're trying to send to India? Well, I
haven't studied Pakistan's nuclear
doctrine. Do they have a document out in
public what about what what the nuclear
doctrine is? I don't know.
Uh their strategic perspective is that u
they need this great enemy called India.
Um and they can then use that to to
acquire foreign investment from nations
who don't want India to grow which is
nations like the US and China. They
always want a foreign master. They are a
mercenary nation and their nuclear
doctrine is that we will that it's the
it's a doctrine of nuclear blackmail. We
will keep on doing terrorism but if you
attack us will use nuclear weapons.
That's the nuclear doctrine. Um
and well that that's what it is. I don't
know beyond that what to say. What's the
real message they're trying to send to
India? Uh the real message is that of
nuclear blackmail as far as I see. I
don't know if any other message they're
trying to send India. And of course that
has fallen flat on its face during
operation sindu because we hit them so
hard and all their nuclear red lines
which they had been tomtoming about were
crossed and yet what
Shihaji says if Hindu gods exist why
they didn't know medical science I don't
know how to answer this question so
Tarun says I am a 22-year-old software
engineer I don't see any future except
climbing corporate lad ladder I feel I'm
not born to work for corporate till 60
good and passion about math. Suggest me
how to get out of red rat race.
The corporate ladder. Yeah. It means
that you work for a corporation. I don't
know what your interests are, but you're
going to now get into the corporate
world and you will do as you told and
you'll be you'll make that part of your
life and you'll be make that the primary
part of your life. That is the corporate
ladder. I've been there. I've been a
cyber for a decade. I hated it
and I got out of it and it was a tough
transition but I got out of it.
So yeah, I also knew uh that was not for
me to work as a slave essentially a high
paid slave for somebody who will tell
you what to do. You always have a master
to serve until you're 60 and then you
sit down and die eventually. That's
that's not for me. And I suppose you you
also see it that way. You passion
passionate about math and so on. How to
get out of the rat race? The only viable
way to get out of the rat race is to be
financially self self-sufficient, which
means you need to have your own source
or sources of income that are pretty
much redundant,
which could mean that you start a
business of your own. Well, I'm not sure
if that's something that you are good at
because you need to learn how to do a
business, how to run a business, and
that that comes with complexities of its
own. That also can turn you into a slave
of your of of your own work if you're
not careful. Unless you hire people and
have them do the work for you, which is
very hard to do because it's very hard
to find the good good people in this
country in India and so on. But if you
don't want to work for somebody until
you're 60, you need to find you need to
create your own sources of income,
whatever they are. Uh how do you create
sources of income? You have to look into
your strengths. What are your strengths
and aptitudes? What are what I what are
I really good at? And then you leverage
that to provide some kind of value to
society and in return for that society
gives you some value back in the in form
in the form of money. That's generally
how we do it. Uh it's it's not easy. The
easiest thing in the world is to get a
salary. It's like an anesthetic. You get
a salary every month. You go and work.
You work work work work work and you get
a salary every month and you're safe and
you're taken care of until you're not.
Uh yeah. So if you want to get out of
the rat race, you have to take risks.
It's not easy. It's not for everybody.
Uh but you have to find what you're good
at and you have to leverage that to to
get your sources of income.
Uh James says, "Sir, remember you speak
English. Thank the Brits." Well, to hell
with you Brits who imposed this foreign
this abomination of a foreign language
in us. And we shall reject this foreign
language. People like me are mentally
colonized, but hopefully others won't
be.
Cheerio
cursory eclipse. Thank you, sir.
Okay, James
Manikandan Wenard Raman says, "Thank you
for your insight." Okay, thank you. I
listen to your podcast and your courses
from an indic. Final question. What
should we do to upskill/n
both the AI and quantum computing era?
Well, what should we do to upskill the
AI and quantum computing era? Look, you
don't navigate it. You embrace it with
both arms. You embrace it
wholeheartedly.
You make it part of who you are and you
leverage that to leaprog the world. You
can't run from it. You can't hide from
it. The technology is here now. It's
it's not it's not going to go away
anywhere. It's here to stay. So, India
needs to become an early adopter of AI
and quantum computing, right? And I
think we are on the right track. It
looks like we are now
after everything changed after operation
Synindur. So now we are like our our
government officials are like wow we
need to do all this now come on get
going on a war footing AI quantum
computing suburo
that's where we are. So I think India
will do that and as individuals if you
are in in in IT if you're in software if
you're in programming you need to learn
all this stuff right machine learning
all of that stuff quantum computing it's
it's a technology it's not machine
learning but artificial int intelligence
if you want to be an artificial
intelligence developer and do all of
that you need to learn machine learning
and all that which is a pretty tedious
thing but you do do that it'll take you
like to three years to go through all
the course work and so
So yeah so India needs to embrace this
wholeheartedly. India needs to become an
early adopter. India needs to leverage
this instead of running from it. Ankita
madam thank you so much. Thank you.
Financial advisor says this isn't a
geopolitical question but I would be
deeply indebted if you take this. Okay.
What is the course of action you take
when you realize that your parents don't
respect you? Wow. And are knowingly
joining hands with those who have tried
to malign you? Well, I'm sorry that that
could be the case for you. Uh that is
deeply unfortunate.
Okay. So, look, first of all, things
happen. Things don't always go your way.
Sometimes life takes you in in in such
territory. What do you do? For example,
if you have parents who don't respect
you and are knowingly joining hands with
those who are trying to malign you.
Well, first of all, you never do
anything disrespectful to your parents.
Okay? You never do anything that will
hurt or harm your parents. That's number
one.
Whatever it is, they are your parents
and they raised you in whatever way they
could or they did. Okay? Maybe it was
good, maybe it was not good, whatever it
is, but they are your parents. And in
our culture, we never do anything that
disrespects or harms our parents. So,
what can you do then? You have to take
pre you have to take
uh steps
which are which are in self-defense,
right? Forget about not respect you. But
if they they are doing something that
will harm you and they're joining hands
with those who have maligned you then
you first of all say
don't disrespect them don't harm harm
them don't do any anything that will
hurt them but you need to put some
distance between you and them right
that's what I would say so put yourself
in a position where they can no longer
hurt you or harm you is all I will say
maybe move to a different city and um I
don't know how you do it is up to you
this is a very unusual thing But u yeah
take adequate measures self-defense
measures that will ensure that nobody
whether the ones who have maligned you
or your parents themselves
could harm you in some way. Uh and of
course this will cause you mental
distress and all. So you will need some
kind of support from other people. Maybe
um I don't know if you have a spouse or
something or I don't know. Yeah. So I
would say the gist of what I'm saying is
that don't do anything that will
disrespect or hurt your parents but take
adequate measures for self-defense in
case they are doing something that will
hurt you or harm you in some way. That's
what that's all I would say sir. All the
best. All the best. I'm sorry that
you're in this situation. All the best.
Uh Pawan Shri Hersha says thank you sir.
Thank you. Uh the respect I get as a
research analyst is because of you.
Really? Well okay. Well, thank you so
much Praanchi Pan Shriharaj. Thank you
so much. I'm I'm glad uh whatever I do
has has given you some value and do well
in life, sir. Do well.
Rohit G, thank you so much. I love that
little Groot. I am Groot.
Yeah, that was a good movie, wasn't it?
I am Groot. One of the original ones. Uh
Shind says, I don't think all
polytheistic societies were like
Hinduism. uh many like Arab Arab pe
paganism or habaism were distinct
indigenous systems rooted in their own
lands and they had no connections with
Vic Hinduism. I have never made the
claim that everything was connected to
Vic Hinduism.
Do you think that Tangism for example
what the what is called in English
Tangism? Do you think it had any
connection with Vic Hinduism? It did
not. It had no connection to Vic
Hinduism. It evolved entirely
separately, entirely independently.
But as a polytheistic culture, it has so
many characteristics that are
interchangeable with Hinduism.
Do you think Shinto in Japan
had any original initial connection with
Vic Hinduism? None whatsoever. It
evolved entirely independently and
separately from Hinduism in Japan.
But once again
it has so many characteristics that are
actually pretty interchangeable with
Hinduism. So polytheistic societies
have common elements that are
interchangeable but they also have
distinct elements that are not
interchangeable.
So in some cases you will have
polytheistic cultures that are very
different.
In some cases you will have politic
cultures that evolved differently
thousands of kilometers apart but are
super similar
like for example Shinto and Hinduism
super similar.
The the Shinto writers used to say that
Buddhism
I mean when they compared Hinduism,
Buddhism and Shinto they said Buddhism
is is not like Shinto but Hinduism is
like Shintto way more like Shinto. So
you have Japanese literature that that
speaks about this. And once again when
it comes to for example Tangism they
have elements that are very similar to
Hinduism ancient Hinduism they have
skyfather and earth mother. Skyf father
is Tangri earth mother is um in ancient
Hinduism we had the sky father father
Ditru and we had the earth mother
pritimata. Same thing
we also had the the the
reverance of ancestors and reverance for
forests and trees and all that in very
ancient Hinduism. We still have it in
even more modern versions of Hinduism.
So there's a lot of elements that are
common and similar and that's why these
cultures are very you know they can
syncretize very easily if if required
but I'm sure Arab paganism was
different. Yeah. So you know it depends
it depends on so many different contexts
and please I have never claimed that all
polytheism has roots in Vic Hinduism. I
have never made that claim. Okay in case
is if that's what you're trying to say.
I have never made the claim.
I'm not stupid.
Mira says what is good about Israeli
agro technology? Many of her MPs went to
study it. Why is it not implemented in
arid areas of India? Not sarcasm. Trying
to understand. Oh no of course not
sarcasm.
See, Israel is mostly desert land. Okay,
a lot of it is desert land. They have
some green patches and all olive trees
and kibbutis and kibbutim and so on. But
lot of lot of the land in Israel is
arid. So what they do is they have
excellent desalination technology in
which they take water from the sea,
desalinate that, dump the brine back
into the ocean and take the fresh water
out of it and that can be used for
agriculture and so on. and they have
developed very good uh desalination
technology. I suppose you can even drink
that water. So that's one example of
something you can use in India in arid
parts of India for example in Rajasthan
in Katch or wherever else where you have
lack of water or sufficient water.
So I believe lots of our MPs and chief
ministers have gone studied that I don't
know why it's not implemented in various
parts of India. I think the government
of India needs to answer it. If you have
sent MPs and chief ministers who have
gone and who have been studying this for
more than two decades, what happened?
Why has this not been implemented in
India? I'm sure the Israelis are happy
to sell the technology to India. That's
not a big deal. It's not a jet engine
technology. They can sell it. Uh so
that's one example of what's good. you
know, I'm sure there are other examples
of Israeli technology which u would also
involve uh you know how to have good
agricultural output in arid land areas.
So I'm sure they have other things also
that they have been doing and I'm sure
we can implement those in India. But the
one example I know of is this
desalination technology in which you can
take water from the sea, desalinate it
and use that water for maybe drinking
purposes or agriculture. that should
definitely be implemented in places like
Kutch for example that have a sea coast
but are are very arid so I'm sure that
can be done so why is it not implemented
I think the government of India needs to
answer a lot of this the government of
India so much money is used for all
these things go MPs going and studying
various other countries and the
technologies but then what happens I'm
not sure what happens
France Beckenbar the the German the
German colonel of Foothwall says have
you read about the battle of Kchel
kingdom of Travancor against the Dutch
how powerful were the Dutch is this
battle caused a downfall I I have not
read this sorry
yeah my my interest in Indian history
goes back to ancient Indian history like
really ancient and that's not studying
history it's kind of researching history
I don't know about the battle of culture
I am not interested at all I have never
been interested in the colonial period
which which I've always seen as as a
time of misery. I've always been
interested in victories and greatness.
So I've always wanted to study the part
of the the the period of history that is
not very very well known. So I I don't
know about the battle battle of culture,
the kingdom of Tvankor against Dutch.
I'm sure it was great. I'm sure the
these battles were great and we fought
very well. But I am not aware of the
details. So I am very sorry. I'm not
able to answer this question. I've not
studied this.
Uh Samir Bhagwat says recent Chinese
aggression against India, art of war.
Which Chinese aggression are you
referring to? Uh it's been a while since
we had galwan. Uh beyond that now they
are essentially siding with Pakistan.
Art of war everything is art of war. Art
of war is not some great book. Okay?
It's a book of strateg. It's a book of
tricks. It's not a book of strategy.
It's not a book of geostrategy. It's a
book of tricks. Strategems.
Let me Google in case. Well, let's
Google it. What's the difference between
strategy and strategy? Okay. The art of
war is a book of strategems. It's a book
of tricks, like I say. Okay. Strategy
versus strategy. There we have it. So,
strategy, a strategy is a broad
overarching plan to achieve a long-term
goal. And a strategy is a specific,
often clever tactic or trick used within
the strategy. So, like I said, strategys
are tricks. The art of war is a book of
tricks. It's not a book of grand
strategy.
So the the west has overhyped this art
of war by Sunzu. What who did Sunzu
fight by the way? If he ever existed, he
said to have existed about 2 and a half
thousand years ago. Well, who did
Sununzu fight if he existed?
He fight he fought his fellow Chinese.
He never fought foreigners and so on.
Uh Prashant says is Boeing too big to be
taken to court if proven.
I think it's about US law. I think
anybody can be taken to court. But if
there are too many vested interests and
if too many American politicians have
their pockets being filled by Boeing
because America is the world's most
corrupt country, in that case nothing
will ever happen.
If a lot of US politicians are in the
pockets of Boeing, which is likely, then
nothing will happen to Boeing. they'll
keep on manufacturing substandard
aircraft and unfortunately more such
things may happen in case this had
something to do with that but yeah so in
the US it's like that okay everybody is
interconnected especially politicians
are are connected with the various
companies and u they are financed by the
companies which means that they will
take care of the companies when it comes
to forming laws and and when it comes to
lawsuits and all that so I think Boeing
will be Okay.
Memes codes tell us about the history of
six and their importance.
I don't know much about the history of
sex. Okay. I've not studied the the 10
gurus and the origins and all that. I
know that they the sik kingdom was a big
kingdom. Some people called it the sik
empire. It wasn't large enough to
actually be called an empire in my
opinion. I'm just just look at the
geography. But their greatest king was
Maharaja Ranjit Singh. Truly great man.
He did fight the invaders and kick them
out of Kashmir, the Pashons, the Abdales
etc. Great man and he was the one great
king they had. Of course they had many
other great warriors and all that. Um
and the sik people are not an ethnicity.
That's just a a religious punt of of
dharma and that has so once Maharaja
Rajit Singh passed away the kingdom
disintegrated very rapidly and the
British took over and after that well
well you know how things have been
being enlight
says why are we technologically
advancing to a world where humanity is
obsolete
Is calamity or global economic meltdown
the only thing that could slow or
reverse technological advancement like
the Bronze Age collapse?
Well, I'm not sure if humanity needs to
be obsolete or if technology should
necessarily or will necessarily make
humanity obsolete. What we are going
towards is we are now at an uh at a
point maybe an inflection point where
machines are able to do things that
humans only humans could do in the past.
So we have artificial intelligence which
thus far seems to be prediction machines
okay that can predict the next most
likely uh character that needs to be
output. That's the large language models
LLMs but they are becoming increasingly
more more and more sophisticated. Apple
claims that they are not really
reasoning models. Some of them they just
still statistically putting out the most
likely next token and all that but but
these are very powerful systems now and
they can really solve big problems
possibly scientific problems uh they so
and so on so forth all of that is
happening. So a lot of of human
intellectual capital is now being
replaced by artificial intelligence. And
if you see that in the light in of the
developments and advances we are we are
now seeing in robotics and if you marry
the two technologies together AI and
robotics then it it's a completely
revolutionary inflection point in human
history. So very soon you will have
intelligent robots doing stuff that
humans used to do. So yeah, that could
make a lot of human labor redundant. It
doesn't mean that humanity needs to
become obsolete. So it'll all depend. So
the problem is this that most of the
world depends on the system of
capitalism that you have to do labor in
order to have wages,
right? And if you don't have a job,
which means you can't contribute labor
to somebody, then you have no right to
any wages, which means you will starve.
That's kind of the system. And there are
failsafe mechanisms like um like like
like u government takes care of you and
there's this basic uh income that they
can give you universal basic income.
That's a concept that's being floated
around and so on. So yeah because so
it's the technology is not making
humanity obsolete. It is the system of
capitalism
that requires you to contribute labor
without which you don't get money. And
then money is the currency by which you
acquire goods and services. So that's
why and food. So that's the problem. The
problem is capitalism. I am not saying
Marxism is the solution. By the way, I'm
not saying that. Don't look at the world
from a in a in this bipolar perspective.
Black or white, capitalism or communism.
If you say capitalism is bad, then
Marxism and communism is right. I am not
saying that. There has to be other ways.
Uh so it's the system that is in in in
is making humanity obsolete potentially.
It's not technology that's doing it.
It's capitalism that's doing it.
Um so what could slow down? See why do
we need to reverse technological
advancement? I think technological
advancement is fantastic.
I mean imagine technology takes care of
everything. All the human labor, need
for human labor is gone. And humans can
finally relax and sit in peace and do
something higher, higher thinking and
higher creativity and all that. That can
only happen if if if that condition is
no longer there that unless you do hard
labor, you don't get any wages, right?
So what's the solution? Is the solution
a universal basic income?
Maybe that's not the right solution
because that once again comes under the
ambit of capitalism in which case some
most people get a universal basic income
you know barely bare survival and some
people become super super rich and
powerful. Once again that's not right.
So we need some other system. The
solution is not slowing down or
reversing technology development. The
solution is not something else like
collapse the bronzes bronze edge
collapse. The solution is to develop
some kind of system
that that respects human life and the
the value of human life and is not a
capitalistic system without becoming a
Marxist or communist system. Some kind
of solution needs to be found. So it's a
very interesting question that you have
posed over here.
Shashank says, "Humans are known to have
originated in Africa, but is it possible
for species to be born in such desert
climate or is it different or was it
different at that point in time?" It's a
good question you asked, sir. It's a
good question. I'm glad you as question.
Let's go to the map.
Let us go to the map and and try and
find out what the deal is. Great
question, Shashank.
So, look,
so where did humanity evolve? It is said
to have emerged
somewhere in eastern Africa. Somewhere
in Eastern Africa, maybe Ethiopia, maybe
Kenya, maybe Tanzania, maybe somewhere
around this region. Okay,
somewhere here. And much of this is
today deserted. You're right. Look at
the satellite images.
See, look at that barren.
There is some green, but there's a lot
of brown, a lot of red, which is red
rock, and so on. So as you can see
there's a darth of water and all that.
So the question that Shashank is
rightfully asking is that and and if you
look at other parts of Africa I mean
look at the amount of desert that we
have here. Who survives?
Who can survive? Even here you have
Nabib in the Nabib desert and all that.
So the question is
how can a species like humanity emerge
originate in such a drastically harsh
climate?
And the question is, was the climate
different at that point in time? Well,
you see, the climate has always changed.
About 80,000 years ago or something,
this entirety of this desert over here,
the Sahel region desert, the Sahara
desert, it was green. It was lush green.
You had lakes over here. You had forests
all over the place. It was completely
lush green. And then desertification
happened. So the point is that you know
what is this nice place? Some kind of a
lake. The the point is that you have
these climatic cycles desertification
and aforestation and again
desertification again aforestation. This
happens over and over again.
And in the past you had forests in the
parts of Africa that are currently uh
all desert. And once again let me tell
you something else. when the art of
Africa migration happened which is said
to have happened about 80,000 or so
years ago plus or plus or minus it is
said to have happened over here the
straight of Bab al- Mandib okay so it's
about I don't know what it's not very
wide it's less than 30 km wide and it is
said that the human migration happened
from here out of Africa so if you look
at the Arabian Peninsula today it's all
desert all desert right but about 70
80,000 years ago all of the coastal
regions were were forested
So the migration happened along the
forested coastal regions and there was
probably a a crossing of the straight of
Hormuz over here and once again the
coast of Balojasthan was all green and
the humans they followed the greenery
until they reached this gigantic green
place which is the Indian subcontinent
and that's where humanity first settled
properly. So today if you look at u the
the Arabian peninsula and all that it's
all desert. So you you'll say how did
humans migrate in this regions but
because it was different at the time you
see so the answer to your question
Shashank is that the the climate has
always kept changing climate change is a
natural process plus today a human
mediated process. So it was different at
the time and humanity evolved over
millions of years. The human chimpanzeee
split happened what two three million
years ago and we've had various kinds of
archaic humans who developed over time
homo erectus homohabilis homo this homo
that homohes
and today we have homo sapiens and so on
so
um Shrii says I'm curious about if
you're doing content creation full-time
or also finding time for theoretical
physics I find it difficult to manage my
time I am not doing a lot of theoretical
physics these days yeah it's something I
need to return to eventually
Not right now. Yep. Not much time for
that right now unfortunately. And I I
would love to have time only for that
actually.
Being enlight says
Chhatrapati Shambaji Maharaj's
achievements and sacrifice commitments.
Um look once again I have not studied
Maratist that much so I will not be able
to give you details about that.
Philosophic Shadow says is doing CFA a
good career option for a 19year-old?
What is CFA?
I am Let me Google what is CFA? What is
CFA? CFA.
What is CFA? Chartered financial
analyst. Okay. Is doing a chartered
financial analyst thing good career
option. Hey, it's money.
I think you I think there's a lot of
money in that in that career. So, if if
money is what you want, I I would say go
for it, sir. you'll make a good amount
of money in that. Anything that has to
do something to do with with with
finance
and so on, I think there's a lot of
money in that. Okay. So, if that's if
that's what you what you want, then I
think it's a good option. Gary says,
"What are your thoughts on the Sikh
Empire?" Look, once again, like I said,
I have not studied the history of the
Sikh Empire in any detail at all, but I
think it was a great
rather short-lived empire, but a great
empire. The one great king the Sikh
empire had was the great Maharaja Ranjit
Singh. He um
he he totally punished the the Pashons
for what they had did what they had done
in Punjab uh in in in in Kashmir. He
liberated Kashmir from the Pons. He
brought Dharma back to the to to the
Kashmir region. He also punished the
Pashons by taking some Pon territory
which today is the Kaiba Pakuna region.
The border of the Sikh Empire,
the the western border of the Sikh
Empire is the present day border between
Pakistan and Afghanistan and it is
Maharaja Ranjit Singh's conquest of the
present day hyberakuma region which is
the root cause of the territorial
dispute between Afghanistan and
Pakistan.
But overall I think the Sikh Empire was
a was a brilliant unfortunately
short-lived empire a lot of good things
in it. one of the great kings Maharaj
Rajit Singh and he was a he was a very
good king no question about it very
valerous great warrior he had a very
meritocratic approach I believe to
governance and the military affairs he
had many great warriors who who fought
for him and unfortunately after his
death didn't didn't go well at all and
within a decade the whole empire had
collapsed the British had destroyed
Cursory clips says uh do you think
Israeli Israel controls the US USS
Liberty incident? The USS Liberty
incident happened in the six- day war
right 67 or somewhere around that time
in which the Israelis attacked and and
struck a US warship the USS Liberty with
missiles maybe air strikes I don't know
what it was many u soldiers many many
sailors died apparently and so on so
yeah that that's something that happened
and Israel apologized and paid some
restitution and that was it and there
was no action that was taken by the US
against Israel
Do I think that that Israel controls the
US? Well,
I I don't know.
I don't know.
Uh Mugi Vara says, "Uh, namaste, sir. My
top 10 most influential persons ever."
Okay. Who are the most influential
people of all time? In ancient times,
you had Lord Ram, Lord Krishna for sure.
Gotham Buddha sure no question.
Zaratustra definitely uh Alexander
Julius Caesar yes I would say still
remembered whether you like it or not.
Yes. Uh u
if Mr. Christ existed then he definitely
was a very influential person Mr. Jesus
Christ. If the who else I would one one
one has to say the prophet Muhammad also
no question about it. the second largest
religion today all because of of his
teachings. So there is that and uh who
else do we have
most influential
people's people's people persons how how
many did they give you most influential
and then in in the 20th century you have
musicians who become super influential
the Beatles
super influential and so on so something
went wrong in the 20th century and
people started worshiping entertainers
Elvis Presley the Beatles
and so on.
Who else could be the most influential
person? So, I'm sure I'm missing a few,
but if you put me on the spot like this,
you'll get a few answers. So, maybe
yeah, there
Surya Pawan says, "Don't leave YouTube,
sir. Make videos until 2050." 2050.
We'll see about that. We'll see about
that. But anyway, thank you. 2050. Vin
Jooshi says, "Can micro needling bring
lost hairs back?" I have absolutely no
idea. No idea. Sorry.
Querty, you etc. says, "If humanity
started from just one place and only a
couple of people in breeding over
generations would cause genetic issues
and more diseases." So, I'm sure it was
not just a couple of people. The story
of Adam and Eve, it doesn't make sense,
right? Obviously, from a scientific
perspective, it would start from one
place, but it it would start with one
community, and it would be a sizable
community
of of of individuals. Apes. Apes. So
maybe you had in Africa in the Rift
Valley region a population of let's say
20,000 apes
who were the ancestors the common
ancestors of today's humans and
chimpanzees. And then over a few
thousand years the rift valley
went wider maybe over a period of maybe
10 20 30 50,000 years maybe 100,000
years. And slowly these populations
10,000 10,000 drifted apart.
And then you had a population of 10,000
who are related to each other and who
are evolving differently from that other
10,000 population. And that's how maybe
from that population of let's say 10,000
people hypothetically humanity started.
It would not start with a couple of
people. It will start with a community,
a group of people, a group of
individuals. Not just 100, 200. It'll be
a few thousand at least, maybe 10,000.
That way inbreeding will not cause any
big problem. The population density will
be low and uh over time some genetic
drift and migrations will happen and so
on. So that's how it works. It doesn't
start with two people. It starts with a
community of individuals.
Kushav thank you sir. Thank you and
Kushra again. What are your views on
pilot hiring across around the world? I
am planning ATPL
in 2034 from Ira. Will it be a good
time? What what will the visa situation?
I don't know what is ATPL. I don't know
what is it. Let's me see what these
things are.
Okay. What is ATPL? ATPL. What is ATPL?
Airline transport transport pilot
license. Highest form of pilot
certification required for pilots who
act as captain and first official
commercial airlines and so on so forth.
What is IO? E R A U. What is IO?
Embry Riddle.
Embry Riddle Aeronautical University.
Where is Embry Riddle? Riddle. Where is
it?
It is um Daytona. Is it Florida? Is it
okay? Daytona Beach, Florida. Okay.
Fine. Okay. So, that's the plan that you
have.
So, what's my views on pilot hiring
across the world? I I have no idea about
this this industry and what the
situation is like. Um
2034 you planning. Why not next year?
Why not this year? Why why 9 years down
the line? Or maybe you're you're very
young perhaps. Okay. Will it be a good
time? What about the visa situation? I
have no idea. 10 years is is too long a
time to make any kind of forecasting.
The visa situation may not be great. The
Americans are cracking down on all all
all foreigners. Um at least the Trump
regime is is doing that. They don't like
foreigners. They want all foreigners
out.
um they are all ma ma make America great
again that sort of thing so I don't know
what the visa situation will be like in
2034 I think it's too far away for us to
make any kind of forecastal predictions
I think we definitely will need pilots I
don't think u
aircraft will become automated by that
time in 9 10 years maybe it's a little
too early for that especially when it
comes to transporting hundreds of people
you can't have an AI and a robot doing
So hopefully pilots will still be
required but I think it's it's 2034 is
too far away for me to make any kind of
forecast. It's it's just too far away.
Um Mr. Sid says what is that one
geopolitical event that would change the
world order completely? What should
India do to grow and become more
powerful? One geopolitical event that
would change the world completely.
It's a technological breakthrough of
some kind. It's always going to be a
technological breakthrough of some kind.
Right now, the US is leading in AI, in
robotics. China is trying its best to
catch up. It's at number two right now.
But what if a nation somewhere develops
some kind of technology that is
completely different from everybody else
and it gives them
a staggering unfair advantage over
everybody else.
Let's say you develop anti-gravity.
Okay, just just a wild example.
Let's say you develop anti-gravity which
gives you the ability to instantaneously
on demand put hundreds of spacecraft
into orbit.
How about that? And in in so you
suddenly leaprog NASA, you leaprog
SpaceX, you leaprog everybody and you
can have
bases on Mars in two years just like
that. No need for the chemical rockets
which are dangerous and which can
explode. You just have anti-gravity. You
just make a proper wellsealed
spacecraft and you just use the
anti-gravity mechanism to go all the way
into orbit and beyond orbit and go
wherever you want.
That would possibly even give you access
to asteroids and their their minerals
and all that
very quickly.
If let's say hypothetically India
develops that, then all of a sudden
India is in space, India dominates
space,
India can take out anybody's satellites
that we want on demand
and so on. So it's always be always
going to be some kind of technological
breakthrough that comes from nowhere
that will change the world order
completely. Nothing else will. It's
always going to be a technological
breakthrough.
Okay.
Right. Where was I? Let me find where I
was.
Okay. So, interesting question sir.
Vun says patchamama of the Andes
translates to green mother goddess of
well-being nature. It's same as pachai
amman of tamila. No not necessarily not
necessarily too many parallels. There
are so many parallels like that in the
world. Pa mama means earth mother not
green mother. How do I know this?
Because one of the founding fathers of
the Inca Empire, he called himself
Pacuti.
What does Pakuti mean? The earth shaker.
Patcha means earth. Pakuti means earth
shaker. Similarly, patcha mama means
earth mother, not green mother. And mama
is a Spanish word. It's not an inca
word. Patcha is an inka word. So there
are these coincidences and similarities.
It doesn't mean necessarily anything at
all. Okay. And I mean one of their kings
was called Vira Kocha and Indians will
say oh it is Virrochina Vrochina. Let's
please let's be a little more mature.
That's not how it is. So I I disagree
with this. Okay. Patcha patcha mama does
not mean something like something
uh patcha aman or whatever it is. Okay.
Okay. Okay. Okay. Let's let's where was
I? Where was I? Which question was I on?
One second. Give me a second. Okay, here
it is. All right. Okay. Nut says, "Lots
of youth in India waste time dooms doom
scrolling reals, video games. Millions
of them spend 10 plus years preparing
and writing for exams in the hopes of
getting sarcas."
So these are two diff very different
things. the doom scrolling and reels and
all that's one thing and uh this this
spending your decades what decade of
life preparing for exams and writing
exams over and over again IAS or
whatever every year how many is
positions are open about about a
thousand 2,000 and hundreds of thousands
millions of Indians try for that
and at the end of the day you end up
being a sarcer right you end up taking
orders from a politician
But you get this feeling that you know I
am a I'm a bureaucrat. I'm a powerful
person and so on. So that's a different
story from the real and doom scrolling
and video games and all that. Totally
different.
Why do Indians want to have the circar
no this this government job? Because
it's job for life. No matter what you
do, you're going to have a job until
you're what 60some
and there's the possibility of making
tremendous amounts of money allegedly.
through alleged means. You know what the
alleged means are, right? So that's why
Indians is lots of Indians want this.
Uh what what's the solution to that? The
solution to that is to have lots of
opportunities in all kinds of sectors
beyond the the government jobs.
So everybody as as a child has some
dream, right? Somebody wants to become a
pilot, somebody wants to become an
astronaut, somebody wants to become a
scientist or doctor or something. But
then once you reach a certain age,
reality st stares in the face and you
have to become either a corporate slave
or you have to become a government
servant. Very few options. So if you
have lots of options in society, lots of
different kinds of jobs that are
available and you don't have to stick to
one job for the rest of your life. You
can choose you can change careers if you
want after every two three years. Then
you then people will not need feel the
need to become a sari babu a government
servant. And the other thing that that
needs to happen is a war on corruption.
So that that aspect also goes away.
That's one thing. Uh about reals and
video games and all. I don't know what
to be done about that. Um
that's a whole different story.
Uh what can you make people embrace
reality for? I think you know um
in today's day and age see every every
generation is different. People who grew
up in the 60s, they had a different life
from those who grew up in the 80s and
they had a different life from those who
grew up in the 2000s and they have a
different life from those who grow are
growing up right now. So every
generation is different. The
technological paradigm is different and
today is the the age of the screens,
right? There's nothing you can do about
it. So I think it's it's something we
have to accept that today's kids are
going to be hooked to screens. Of
course, it's great if they spend some
time outside and do some actual actual
playing and having fun. Imagine today
you to force kids to go out and play. In
the past, you had to force kids to come
home and study. Today, it's a opposite.
But some kind of solution needs to be
found. Maybe some kind of time limit on
screens and all that perhaps. I think it
it's something parents have to impose on
their own individually. Animeh says, "As
a busy tech tech worker, how can I build
intellectual acumen and broad knowledge
to one day pursue what I truly truly
love?" Well, first of all, thank you,
sir. Um,
you're a busy tech worker. A lot of time
you spend doing whatever you do as a
tech worker, but you want to build
intellectual acumen and the broad and
deep knowledge that's required to
someday pursue whatever it is that you
truly love. I don't know what that is
but okay maybe it's something that needs
a lot of knowledge broad as well as
deep. What do you do? What you do sir is
you find some time in your life beyond
working and sleeping and whatever else
you do maybe an hour or two every day
that you that you spend
absorbing this knowledge gaining this
knowledge and the only way to gain
knowledge is is to read. The only real
way to gain knowledge is to read. Let me
be very very very very honest with you
all. Okay? I do podcasts, don't I? I've
done more than 90 podcasts. As a host of
a podcast, so I'm a podcast host. I'm
also I've also been a podcast guest on I
don't know hundreds of podcasts.
You will never gain deep knowledge from
a podcast.
Okay, I'm giving you a very honest truth
here. A podcast is something that will
perhaps introduce you to new knowledge
and maybe it's something that will start
your fascination
about a certain topic or a field or an
area of knowledge or a domain of
knowledge. But if you watch a 100
podcasts about quantum computing, never
you'll never learn quantum computing. If
you watch a 100 podcasts about
theoretical physics, you will never
really learn good theoretical physics.
So a podcast is a good introduction to a
subject. It's it can also be good
entertainment if it's you want to be
entertained and you you like certain
topics but you can never learn a subject
in great depth. So what you have to do
sir is you have to read. You have to
read. Reading is difficult. Reading can
be really difficult. It can be really
taxing on the mind. But the only way to
gain deep knowledge is by reading and
perhaps even writing. So that's what you
have to do if you want to build the
intellectual acumen and broad knowledge
and perhaps deep knowledge to pursue
something that you truly love in the
future. You have to invest an hour or
two every day. Somehow you you to find
the time or maybe a certain amount of
hours per week you to find to do the
hard work of of of acquiring the
knowledge and the information. That's
what you have to do. Okay. Anime all the
best sir.
CPTV says how many missile boats does
our navy navy need right now? They are
building six. By the way, that's a great
question. I'm a big fan of missile
boats. A missile boat is a super cheap
way of delivering missiles to to where
they need to be delivered.
So, let's say and a missile boat doesn't
have to be very expensive. I suppose you
can build a missile boat for let's say
$20 million. A missile boat that can
have three bramos missiles on it. You
can engineer it properly in in such a
way that it will cost you maximum $20
million including the engine, including
everything. And it doesn't have to have
very long legs and very long endurance
runons. It can be kind of a coastal
beast.
Maybe it can have an endurance of let's
say let's say 1,000 km,
you know, the sort of legs. Maybe
endurance of 30 days if you can
replenish it properly. That's that's
plenty for a missile boat.
So if you have a missile board that
costs $20 million, not including the
Brahos missiles
then 20 million and if you'd have 10
it's 200 billion. If you have 100 it's 2
billion 2 billion is not a big amount of
money for a 100 missile boats boss.
So why not have a 100 missile boats you
just spend $2 billion
and of course each missile boat will
have to house three bramos missiles. I
mean that's a frightening thing if you
are an enemy of India. A 100 cheap
disposable missile boats that can
puncture your ships and slice them into
pieces. So I think the more the marrier.
Six. What is six? Where's the ambition?
What is six missile boats? What are we
Sri Lanka?
I think we need more. We should have at
least 50 submarines. At least 100. I
would say 300 missile boats. If I was in
charge, I would say 300 missile boats.
Of course, I'll I'm sure it's a little
excessive, but I would say we should
have a 100 missile boats, okay? And 50
submarines and other various kinds of
other assets. So, I would say 100
missile boats and make sure that none of
them costs more than $20 million a
piece. So, a total of $2 billion, which
is not a big amount of money, and you
get a 100 scary dangerous assets. Well,
what else can you ask for? Uh,
Phonography says, "Have you read KL
Jung?" What are my thoughts? I haven't
read KL Jung. Sorry, I haven't had the
time to read KL Jung. That's a very
Jordan Peterson thing, right? KL Yung,
the shadow shadow self and all that. I
have some some kind of awareness of what
he wrote about, but I haven't read it in
detail. Sorry. Likit Shri Nath says, "Is
a pilot job still in good demand for
freshers?" I I don't know. I don't know.
It's not part of my worldview about what
what the job market is like and what the
demand is like uh for more pilots in the
country. I'm not aware sir. I am not
aware. Sorry.
Argarapatim Roy. Thank you so much sir.
Thank you. And Argapatim Roy again a
question. Do you think this ch do you
think there's a chance we might have to
go we might have to go up again Israel
in the future? Will India be able to
counter Mossad sabotage operation in
India? Let's not even discuss this.
Okay. uh Israel is not some all all
weather friend of India's but Israel is
not an enemy of India's
whatever I say about Israel and and I
point out various things it's not to
portray Israel as an enemy I don't think
I don't see Israel as an enemy of India
all I am saying is that Israel is not an
unconditional friend of India's Israel
has its own interests its own agendas
which every nation should have and we
have our own separate interests and
agendas there's a lot of convergence
which is why India and Isra Israel work
together. Okay. And there is divergence
as well which is why Israel shows
certain kinds of maps of India and
sometimes India votes against Israel in
the United Nations. That's how it works.
You can't have a convergence of all
interests any ever for two nations. My
point is I want to wake up Indians who
are deluded and they believe that Israel
is an is is is an unconditional friend
of India. There are no unconditional
friends of India. There are no
unconditional friends anywhere in
geopolitics. That's what I want to
that's the message I want to drive drive
home for the Indians who seem to be
laboring under various delusions. That's
all. But I am not claiming Israel is a
is an enemy of India's. It's not. So
let's not discuss this. I mean that in
that in that scenario you're trying to
portray
we would be trying to portray Israel as
an enemy which it is not.
All I'm saying is that it has its own
agendas and interests which don't always
necessarily align with our interest and
agendas. The best example is Pakistan.
Israel claims that it is an it despises
terrorism. Well, what about Pakistan?
Have you taken any action? Have you even
made any statements against Pakistan?
Not really, right? Not really. And if
you have a problem with a terrorist
nation having nuclear bombs, what have
you done about Pakistan? So clearly it's
not about Pakistan. It's not about
terrorism. It's just that they have an
issue with Iran. Okay.
Vashinda says, "Your thoughts on
Chhatraati Shambaji Maharaj? From the
little that I know about him, I have not
studied Marata history in great detail,
but from the little that I know about
him, he was one of the greatest and
bravest of our of the of the Marata
leaders. That's what I can say. Yeah,
there obviously a very tragic end that
he that he met and a very brave man for
sure. Very great man, very brave man.
Suchin Kandelwal says Iran fired 200
plus ballistic missiles with many more
destroyed along with their proxies.
Essentially Iranians burnt all their oil
revenue. How stupid.
With many more destroyed along with
their proxies. I'm not sure what you
mean by that. So Iran fired more than
200 ballistic missiles.
Iran burned all their oil revenue. I'm
not sure what what the connection is
over here.
Um, and why is it stupid?
If you are hit, if you are targeted by
an enemy, you got to do something about
it, right?
You got to do something about it. How is
it stupid? I'm not sure how it is
stupid. So, I'm not able to get the
logic.
Uh, portfolio says, give your thoughts
on Iran Israel strikes. Iran Israel
strikes.
Um so this is something I kind of
expected if you've seen my geost
strategy episodes it is one of the the
scenarios which has a significant
probability of happening and now it's
happened right so Israel
struck at Israel Israel struck at Iran
they tried a decapitation strike they
targeted much of Israel's top leadership
Mr. Beri apparently has been taken out.
They struck at the Natan's nuclear site
and so on exactly as per one of the one
of the scenarios that I had forecast
right and um Iran obviously had to hit
back. Now it looks like the Israelis had
certain assets within is within Iran
that they had positioned there for a
very long time similar to Ukraine's uh
sp operation spiderweb kind of. Yeah.
And then Iran has hit back but they
haven't hit back really hard. some of
their missiles have been intercepted.
Some of them have hit the targets and so
on. So I think it is just an evolving
scenario. It's not something that is
done and dusted. I think it's an
evolving scenario.
And uh I think Iran's reputation is at
stake right now. Iran's credibility is
at stake that Israel has hit them so
hard done what looks like a decapitation
strike on their top leadership and they
the Iranians haven't been able to do
much thus far. So it looks like it's
advantage Israel right now for the time
being where we are right now.
Khali says thoughts on post World War II
order if access won. That's a completely
hypothetical scenario. So in the post
World War II scenario if the Axis powers
won then we would either be speaking
German or Japanese right and Hitler
would be the good guy and Roosevelt and
and the and and Churchill and Stalin
would be would be the bad guys. So if
they access one that's what that's what
the scenario would be like. Uh there is
this serial called
uh I don't remember the name of the I
haven't watched it. I I was aware of it.
So there's this serial in which there is
this alternative history that's
portrayed in which there's the uh the
Germans the Nazis are ruling the US and
that sort of thing.
Man in the high corridors or something
like that. I forget the name of the
thing. Um so yeah it would be a
different world
and maybe we would be speaking German or
Japanese today.
Web says what are ghost particles and
god god's particles. There are no such
thing. These are just names that are
given by the media to various uh
particles in the standard standard model
of physics. I'm not sure what the ghost
particles are. Maybe it's dark matter
they're referring to. They are referring
to neutrinos. Nutrinos are particles
that uh interact only by the weak the by
by the weak force the weak nuclear force
and they are extremely unlikely to
interact with any ordinary matter which
is why they are very ghostly and they
have got very small masses and there
neutral oscillations. What's the
so-called god particle? It's the Higs
particle, the Higs Bzon. And it's the
particle that was u whose ev whose
existence was predicted by Peter Higgs
and a couple of other scientists,
physicists, I think in the 1950s.
And it's the particle that imbused that
that that imbus mass to the universe or
to various particles in the universe and
it was detected only in the 2010s.
So various people have called it the God
particle or whatever. It's not it's not
a god particle. It's just it's just name
that's that's given to it like the big
bang. Fred H oil coined this term big
bang big bang disparagingly
for a rival theory. Fred Ho's theory was
the stud steady state theory of the
universe and he the rival theory was the
expanding universe theory to which he
gave this disparaging name the big bang
but it stuck and we now call it the big
bang theory big bang cosmology. Oh.
Uh, Sumit says, "Can government aravali
plantation stop Thar expansion?" I have
no idea. I haven't looked into it, so I
can't say, but possibly they could if
Yeah. So, can a forest stop the
expansion of a desert? I suppose it can.
If the forest is robust enough and wide
enough and if it is sustained well with
irrigation and all, I suppose it can
stop the expansion of a desert. So, it's
going to be a tugof-war tussle kind of
thing. It depends on how wide and how
robust the forest is and how long it'll
last.
Okay. Memes coder says, "I am from
Hindu/Sik family. We both we follow both
cultures religiously, but I still get
bullied by batchmates as Khal
Khalistani. I love Bat, but how to deal?
That's terrible. That's that's horrible.
Why would they do that? you are from. So
that is so unfortunate that this is the
nonsense that that social media has done
to people. I mean I would say that most
sick people are are are super patriotic
and the sick people are all people same
blood same culture same origin same
everything. How can you just because of
a few rotten apples you cannot start
abusing everybody. So how to deal with
it? Ignore the haters. That's what I
would say. And don't don't let that
nonsense change your love for the
nation. Okay? For the love of the gods.
Don't allow that to happen. And please
remember everybody is not like these
idiots. That's what I would say. Um
yeah. So it's it's just unfortunately
that it's just unfortunate that some
rotten apples
have have caused this problem.
So I would say to you don't allow these
these haters to to affect you. Don't
allow them to change your love for the
country. And you know this is a passing
phase. you don't have to deal with his
idiots forever. That's what I would say.
So stay stay strong and all the best
sir. All the best.
Bradley says there seems to be a wave of
what is it of conservation and
anti-immigration globally. Isn't this
the perfect time for Indians to for
India to throw out its illegals without
criticism?
If we throw out illegals, we will get
criticism. But there is never a better
time to throw out illegals than now. Um
anti-immigration, all of that. Trump
does it. The US is very anti-immigrant
and all that. I think whatever happens,
we should do it. It's time to to start a
mass deportation program for all the
illegal im infiltrators in India. No
question. This is the best time for it.
There seems to be some of that happening
right now. But we need to do it
properly, systematically. Get rid of all
the illegals. All of them.
Uh all the illegal Bangladeshes,
Rohingyas, cookies and Pakistanis and
whoever else may be in India. All the
illegals who have come in illegally, no
matter when they came in, no matter how
many decades before they came in, throw
them out. Needs to happen. So I agree
with you.
Geopolitical Dub says is playing video
games that bad? Why China good at it? I
don't think playing video games is bad.
Everybody needs some entertainment, some
distraction. So there's nothing wrong
with it. What is what can what can be
problematic is if you get hooked to it,
if you get addicted to it and that's all
you do
and and you you do it at the expense of
everything else. In that case, it could
be a problem. Beyond that, what's wrong
with playing video games? There's
nothing wrong with playing video games
or playing football or playing hockey or
playing cricket or whatever play.
Why China good at it? I am not aware of
that. No idea.
Uh Ragavan says there's an interesting
piece of history. Early Alawite, early
Shia Muslims from Syria migrated to
India as early as the 7th century
seeking refuge from persecution. India
has been a haven for diverse communities
and faiths. Okay, I am not aware of this
Alawites coming to India but yeah
certainly possible. India has always
been a haven for diverse communities and
faiths going back thousands of years.
It's always been that way. There's
evidence of immigration into India
during the so-called Harapan era. You
find cemeteries full of first generation
immigrants to India. There is that. Then
when the Romans destroyed the the the
when the Romans destroyed the temple of
Solomon, in Judea, in Jerusalem,
some Jews came all the way to India
seeking seeking refuge in India from
Roman persecution. For 2,000 years,
they've lived in India. their
descendants still live in India today.
Right? Then you we have the the the
Persians who fled from the Arabic
invasion of Persia and they were given
refuge in India in Gujarat and other
play mostly in Gujarat I believe and
they are called the Paris today and they
have been living in India for more than
what 13400 years they were given persec
they were given refuge in India. They
were never persecuted. Neither the Jews
nor the Persians nor anybody else was
ever persecuted in India. Jews have been
living in India for longer than in in
Europe. Not one incident of
anti-semitism in India. Nobody even
knows what anti-semitism is. The Jews
have never been made to change their
religion or culture or way of life.
Never ever ever. Neither the Persians,
the Pars have lived the way they want as
long as they wanted. They've never been
forced to change their their their
lifestyle, their religion and so on.
India has always been the most welcoming
most respect respectful civilization of
all time. Nobody else can come close to
this.
Anul says what's the best way to study
scientifically
by BTWs just read or read and then write
it down like making notes. The latter
one is timeconuming.
That's that's a multi-step approach to
to to study something scientifically to
learn something properly. you first
read.
So when I want to read learn something
new I first read it quickly then read it
slowly and whatever I don't understand I
look into it in detail then I would
write down and see generally when I'm
read learning something it's something
scientific for example if you want to
learn some some new mathematical tool
you first read about it you read what
the what the process is you read what
the technique is what whether it's a new
technique of differential equations or
whatever it is you see you read how the
problems are solved And then you have to
do it yourself. You have to do it
yourself. You first look at the solved
problems and you try try to replicate
that on your own without looking there.
Then once you get some confidence in in
understanding of the technique, then you
look at all the unsolved problems and
then you solve them and then you look at
the answers and see if you've got the
right answers and so on. That's one one
example that I can give you. So um if it
is something else, if it's not math, if
it's maybe economics or something else,
then you read and then you write it in
your own words. And yeah, so it it
depends on what you are learning and and
every every domain, every field has its
own different approach, ideal approach
for learning. But yeah, learning is
timeconuming. No question about it. Um,
of course, when you're reading when
you're learning history, for example,
there's no point reading the history
book and then writing it in your own
words. I never do that. I have never
learned history by writing. Okay? I've
only done it by reading. So, it depends.
It depends on what you're trying to
learn. But the longer you longer time
you spend learning, the better it's
going to be for you. Okay?
Ramnath is complaining. Yeah, I have not
answered this question. Well, when did
you ask this question sir?
Have you as asked this question before?
I haven't seen it.
Okay. The question is, is WTO WTO and
GAT agreement good for India regarding
trade tariff and agriculture? Rajiv Diji
was against
World Trade Organization is an
organization. It's not an agreement.
Okay. Gat agreement. I think it's
obsolete, isn't it? GAT. GAT was
something from the 1980s. What was GAT?
GAT?
What was GAT general agreement on
trades, tariffs and trade? It was
something that was signed in 1947. How
is it relevant today? By the way,
that was something from the 20th
century.
And okay, the Uruguay round of GAT
negotiations led to the creation of the
World Trade Organization, which formally
replaced GAT in 1995.
The WTO provides a more comprehensive
and institutionalized framework for
global trade and so on and so forth.
Okay. So the GAT is something observated
from the 19 from the 20th century.
Um
the World Trade Organization is
obviously something that's going to be
controlled by the West by the US and as
such it's going to impose Western norms
and rules on you.
So obviously it's going to be loaded in
favor of the west and it's going to
benefit the west more than you, more
than India. No question about it. But
the world is ruled by the west. So we
have to navigate the world according to
the rules. That's what China has done
and China has done really well. So we
can we have two choices. We sit down and
cry and complain or we use the existing
system to the best that we can to the
best
extent that we can and we use it to our
advantage. The Chinese haven't cried and
complained and blah boohoo right they
also have faced the same problems that
we are facing but they have done a very
good job and they are in such a power
powerful position today. So my point is
let's stop complaining and crying and
and and use whatever means exist to do
something good for ourselves and and to
advance our position in the world as a
nation as a civilization. And by the way
you I have not seen this question
before. So how can you say that I have
not answered your question? I don't get
it. Why are you complaining sir like
this? I'm happy to answer questions the
moment I see them.
Geopolitan dub thank you so much sir.
Thank you. I always appreciate uh you
very much sir. Pratamesh Kadam, thank
you so much sir. Thank you. Pratamesh
Kadam says, "Have you watched Star
Wars?"
Have I watched Star Wars?
I I was born in 1976,
November.
I first watched Star Wars sometime in
the 1970s.
I must have been 2 or 3 years old.
So I walk into the theater with my dad
and some other relative and Star Wars
has already started. We're slightly late
and what I see on the screen is this big
gorilla. Okay, I'm a little kid. I'm
three I'm two or three years old and I'm
like, "Yeah, gorilla gorilla. It's
actually Chewbacca, the big hairy
creature, the Wookie." But I was
fascinated by Star Wars. I was
captivated. I think that's what began my
my my love affair with science fiction.
I've watched Star Wars. I've watched it
multiple times. I've watched it on the
big screen. I've watched it on on on
regular home TV screens. I've watched it
on those box TV screens, CRT TV screens.
I've watched it on big flat walls world
modern screens and all that. I love it.
I haven't watched I've even seen some of
the new versions of Star Wars. Those
stupid idiotic recent Star Wars movies.
God, I can't stand those.
Uh what
uh the one in which uh Han Solo's son
kills him and that nonsense. Oh god. I I
like the original three. The first one
was great. The New Hope one. The Empire
Strikes Back was outstanding. Part three
was kind of kind of a funnier version,
but it was okay. The the redemption of
Darth Vea and so on. So yeah, I have
watched Star Wars. I have
Pratamesham. Thank you very much. And
once again, okay, I answered your
question, right? Right. I got that.
Harsh Jen says, "How long can Iran fight
back with Israel in the US?" Well, that
that's a good question. Depends on how
many missiles and all that they have and
whether they have nuclear weapons or
not. Depends on that. If you want to
fight a long war, you need supplies. You
need thousands of missiles and drones.
So, it depends on that. And I'm not sure
how many they have. Maybe they have lots
in which case they will last longer
and so on. So ideally they would like to
inflict inflict a comprehensive military
defeat on their enemy and Israel also
would like to inflict a comprehensive
military defeat on Iran. So whoever is
able to do that will end the war and and
prevail. That's how it goes. So Dindra
Desai says what do you think is the
right time to get married when you are a
man with big ambitions? Is it even
necessary to get married? Totally off
topic. Okay.
Is it necessary to get married? I think
it's good good to get married. It gives
you stability in life.
It gives you a support system as long as
you have a good partner. So let's say
you get a good partner and you're lucky.
So what's the good time? What's the
right what's the right time to get
married when you're a man with big
ambitions? I would say in your early 20s
before 25.
Actually
actually that's what I would say. It's
it's the right time for whether you are
a male or a female. The right time to
get married is before you're 25. And
lots of people are going to disagree and
put in the comments. Someday you'll
understand.
But yeah, the right time to to get
married is as early as possible. Get
married, settle down, get the get the
business of having children done as soon
as possible
and and then focus in your career and
have that stability stability at home.
Mugiara says, "If our country makes a
mandatory law regarding army training
for all the citizens, pros and cons, is
there any thought ever given to this by
our government?" Okay, think about it.
Let's say you have mandatory
conscription in military service. Okay,
let's say hypothetically in India. So,
it means that everybody has to
mandatorily
spend a certain amount of time in the
military. Let's say 6 months or or one
year or whatever it is.
What's our population? 1.4 million. How
many military age men
uh become military age every year? A few
million, right? Does the Indian armed
forces
have the bandwidth and infrastructure
and capability and capacity to absorb a
few million boys every year and give
them training for x number of months. I
think if you try to do that, the Indian
armed forces will be overwhelmed.
Because we have so many young men
becoming military age every year.
It's not possible. It's logistically
impossible because of the enormous size
of the Indian population. The Indian
military will be overwhelmed with this.
You understand? Doesn't work for a
country of the size of India.
Goind says according to you which is the
safest country on the world in the world
to live in in terms of every kind of
safety. Well, I don't know. But from my
experience, I would say perhaps
Switzerland. Even Switzerland has now
immigration of various kinds, which is
very sad. Used to be Japan.
I would have said Switzerland and Japan.
But I hear that Switzerland also is now
facing immigration related related
criminal activity. And I hear that there
are there are immigration issues in
Japan also now. So I think the West
wants to rule ruin the whole world I
think by forcing immigration everywhere.
the worst kind of immigration.
Uh but overall I would still say it is
Switzerland and Japan overall. If if
things stay the way they are, I think
these these two nations are still very
safe.
Apart from that, which other nations? 15
years ago, it would have been the Nordic
nation, Sweden, Denmark, all of those
those are scary now because of the kind
of immigrants they've
absorbed.
Uh which other nation is super safe?
Maybe southern American nations. I'm
maybe Argentina perhaps. I don't know.
Perhaps. Okay. I personally haven't been
there so I can't really say but one
hears it's reasonably safe.
Okay. Geopolitical Dubai says, "Sir,
what made you interested in aviation? As
a kid, I was fascinated with aircraft.
As a kid, like when I was like one year
old, I was fascinated with aircraft. I I
wanted to fly. And I still remember the
first time I was in in an airplane. Oh
my god, it was like a dream come true.
Today, it's like you fly all the time.
It's no big deal." But when I was a kid,
it was a huge deal. My god, I am in an
airplane. I'm going to be above the
surface so of the sky of the of the
planet and so on. I was just fascinated
with flying with with airflight with
with aviation all that. I probably think
that my first ambition in life was to
become a become a pilot of some kind
then an astronaut and so on. So it's
something that was always fascinating
for me. So it's always been that way and
I was always interested in aeronautics,
aerodynamics and all that. I used to
make various kinds of very complicated
um model aircraft that could actually
fly and glide and all that and I was
interested in rockets, rocketry,
missiles, all that. So, it's just part
of who I am.
Al says, "How do you master playing
guitar appreciate tips?" Well, that's a
good question and it's a question I
actually can answer. How do you master
playing guitar? First of all, you to
decide whether you want to be a be a
rhythm player or or a lead player. Okay,
rhythm is different. Lead is different.
Rhythm guitar means you're playing
chords. A chord is a combination of
multiple notes. Minimum three and
maximum as many as you want. As many as
fing fingers you can accommodate and you
can play multiple notes at the same time
and so on. U so you would first decide
whether you want to be a rhythm
guitarist or a lead guitarist and you to
try both and you to then then you can
figure out what what you're more
comfortable with or what appeals to you
more. So let's say you have decided you
want to be a rhythm player. Then you
have to start practicing. You know have
a practice routine every day x number of
minutes. The more the better. So let's
say you can practice 30 minutes a day 5
days a week. Well that's not bad. You
will make progress. But if you can
practice 2 hours a day 7 days a week my
god you will make superb tremendous
progress. It depends. And then you need
to have a proper curriculum. Which
chords do you want to practice? Once a
certain set of chords, the basic chords,
the bar chords or whatever become easy
and comfortable for you, then you have
to go to more complicated chords,
augmented chords and diminished chords
and sevenths and fifths and whatever
else, right? Those are jazz chords and
pretty difficult chords to to play and
then you have to incorporate that into
your practice routine and all that. So
that takes time. So you need to have a
proper road map which which will
typically typically extend several
months, maybe 3 months, maybe 6 months.
Once you reach there, then you need to
need to have a daily practice routine,
warm-up routine and so on. If you want
to be a lead lead guitar player, then
you need to have a whole different
approach to that. You need to start with
various uh various scales
and then you to go to other scales. You
start with the scale of C or G or
whatever and you measure you you master
the entire fretboard. Then you start
playing other scales like the mixolidian
scale, the Dorian scale. You can start
practicing experimenting with Indian
ragas for example and so on. So you
going to just keep experimenting keep
practicing there needs to be a complete
foundation for daily daily warm-ups and
practice and then on on top of that you
need to start keep on learning something
new every week and so on so forth. It's
a pretty long journey. It's a lifelong
journey but it's really fun if you're
into it. If you are musically musically
inclined. I used to enjoy really enjoy
playing the guitar. I still have guitars
but these days I don't get the time to
play much. It's been a while since I
played seriously so I must sound like a
beginner suppose I suppose if I try now
but it's great fun. So yeah enjoy all
the best. Black hole says India isn't
held back by China or the US but it's
held back by its own inter internal
corruption at every level from top to
bottom. India is a failed democracy said
too. Um
I would agree with you that India that
the that the biggest problem that India
faces today is corruption. No question
about it. It's the root cause of almost
every problem in India. Whether it is
illegal immigration, whether it is uh
whatever else, whether it is the rot in
the education system, whether it is
whatever else, the root cause is always
it always goes back to corruption. So I
agree
corruption is the biggest problem in
India today and it's something that
nobody wants to speak about right
uh is India a failed democracy I think I
would not entirely characterize it as an
completely failed democracy but the
current system is is not helping India
at all we need a new system a different
system I I would agree with you big big
problems if India has to re reach its
full potential the current system can't
do a thing the current system will not
take us where we need where we need to
be. I agree.
Ganesh guide says what if Pakistan and
Bangladesh don't order open their
borders for illegals. Look most of our
illegals are from Bangladesh, Myanmar,
cookies and a few Pakistanis. If the
Pakistanis are not willing to go, we we
will see. But Bangladesh will have no
choice but to open its borders and the
border with Myanmar is anyway open. So
it's about the will of the government of
India. If the government of India is
willing to kick the illegals out, they
will be out. There is nothing Bangladesh
can do if we are sending the illegals
back. If they try to do something, we
know how to deal with the Bangladeshes.
Okay? And Myanmar will not pose any
problem for us if you want to kick the
illegal cookies out. So it's it's the
the only thing that's that's lacking
perhaps potentially is uh the will of
the government of India. The moment the
government of India decides that they
have to go, they will be gone in
whatever amount of time. Uh Rashi Kudin
says should Hassina be allowed to remain
in India? Yeah, she should be allowed to
remain in India. Yeah, she has been a
friend of India's. She was a good leader
for Bangladesh. She did not do any uh
harm to anybody and she actually put the
the the the the economy of Bangladesh on
on a very good track which is now being
unraveled and so on. So I would say yes,
she should be allowed to remain in India
as a guest. Arin Ja says what is it?
What about climate change 1.5 C already
crossed? Okay, what is 1.5 C?
And what about climate change? What is
climate change 1.5 C? I think it's the
carbon levels in the atmosphere and all
that. Climate change 1.5 C. What is 1.5
C? Oh, 1.5° C Celsius. The first 12
month average. The first 12 12 month
period to exceed 1.5 degrees in average.
Um, okay. Okay. You're talking about
global warming. You're talking about
global warming. Yeah. So, it's crossed
and it's an ongoing issue and there is
absolutely nothing that will be done
about this. Okay. Climate change has two
components. One is a natural component.
One is a human mediated component.
Natural climate change has always
occurred like we discussed earlier in
this episode. Human mediated climate
change is all because of pollution and
the the the the carbon emissions and all
that which is also true. Those who claim
that there is no human component to it
and all that is nonsense. But the point
is how do we stop it? We can't. The only
way we can stop further climate change
caused by humans if is if all the
governments in the world agree to do
certain things and nobody is agreeing
and nobody's going to agree. They will
always prioritize their national
interests. For example, they will say to
India cut down on carbon emissions by
the so and so percentage. We'll say you
have been emitting carbon into the
atmosphere so many decades and centuries
and we need to catch up with you
otherwise we'll always always be left
behind. So we will not stop and they
can't force us to stop and that's the
deal. So it's never going to happen.
Humanity will never unite and it's going
to keep on going. So that's all I can
say about this. Okay, I'm going to do
another 10 minutes and that's that's the
that's it. Okay, so yeah, let's let's
wrap this up sooner rather than later.
Go says, "Why is no one talking about
what's happening in Sudan?" But the UAE,
Western media is not covering it because
of UAE US alliance. Is UAE closer to the
US or China long-term? Which country is
beneficial? etc. Um, the UAE is
definitely closer to the US than to
China. The UAE is also closer to India.
Uh, what's happening in Sudan by UAE?
I'm not aware of the UAE angle. Okay.
I'm not aware of that. I know there's a
disaster situation in Sudan.
Uh, is the UAE behind it? I'm I'm I'm
not sure about that. Um, it's true that
the the media the the media, West media,
Indian media is not covering what's
happening in Sudan. Millions of people
are displaced and there is this
humanitarian crisis. There's the
infighting between two groups in Sudan
between the RAF RAF and the Sudan
government and so on. They're fighting
each other and the civilians are cross
caught in the crossfire and there is no
way of any aid reaching them and it's
it's disaster.
But who's behind this? Well, I'll have
to look into it. Okay.
Um
Charles
Olivera says strip John Duck Jones.
Okay. I don't know what it means but
okay sir if you say so. Bradley says
there seems to be a direct correlation
between difficult languages like
Japanese and lower Islamic immigration.
Also Israel bombed the largest airfield
in Iran. Is it so? Okay. Fascinating.
uh there seems to be direct correlation
between difficult languages like
Japanese and lower Islamic immigration.
No, Japan has always had this policy
that that is strongly against any kind
of immigration. It doesn't have anything
about to do with languages. It's
everything to do with the Japanese
government's policy. It's not like
because the Japanese language is so
difficult that's why fewer immigrants
have gone there. The fact is that the
Japanese government has always had this
policy that we will allow tourists but
we will not allow immigrants. You can't
settle in Japan. No, we don't want
immigrants.
But now somehow the policy seems to have
changed and we know that Japan is
occupied by the US and the US calls the
shots. So maybe the Americans have
decided that now we're going to open up
Japan to to immigration of certain
kinds.
So that's what's happening. Um Israel
bombed the largest oil field. Okay,
maybe it's breaking news. I'll look into
it once this live stream is over. Thank
you for for letting us know. Suchinid
says, "What I meant was Iran invested a
major chunk of its oil revenue in
ballistic missiles. Iran invested a
major chunk of its oil, okay, nuclear
program and its proxy militias, but
Israel destroyed them all." Well, a
nation's got to do what it got to do.
Sometimes it works out for you,
sometimes it doesn't. But at least they
tried. H they knew what enemies they
have and they tried. And you got to
respect them for trying. If it worked,
didn't work, well, that that's up to the
gods.
Um, Govin says, "Is Dubai a safe city to
live in? What aspects of safety are
lacking there that's not known to people
or not covered in media apart from
freedom of speech, PDA, alcohol, etc.?"
Well, I haven't lived in Dubai, so I
can't say. Uh, but from what I hear,
it's it's it's a pretty safe city to
live in, I suppose. I think the UAE
overall is a is a very safe place to
live in. Very little crime, if any at
all. Um, Indians are respected. You have
freedom of of religion. nobody's going
to force it to do something or the
other, any of that. And um
yeah, of course, there are going to be
some restrictions. It's a monarchy. It's
not a democracy. You've got to respect
the local political system. You've got
to respect the local rulers. You've got
to respect the local laws. If you do
that, nobody's going to bother you.
Alcohol and alcohol is available. Yeah,
there's no restriction on alcohol. Uh
PDA, public display of of affection.
Well, it's not the norm in India. It's
not the norm there. So, what's the big
deal? Is it something essential to
living or what? If you want to do
affection, do it at home, right? Why do
you have to do it in public? Freedom of
speech. Which nation is freedom of
speech?
So, I think overall the UA is is is a
good place for Indians to go to and live
in at least temporarily
as far as I know. But I personally
haven't live in Dubai, lived in Dubai.
So yeah, do your own research, do your
own due diligence if you are planning to
uh perhaps potentially move there.
Uh Geopolitical Dubai says, "Can you fly
planes?" No, I have never been inside
the cockpit of an aircraft. I don't know
how to fly planes. Theoretically, I know
how it works, but um yeah, I don't have
any training. None whatsoever. Chir
says, "Israel knew Iran's top gen locks
operation rising lion. How have they not
yet found location of their hostages?
Oh, Iran, Israel knew the locations of
Iran's top generals. How have they not
found the location of their hostages in
Gaja Gaza? Well, that's that's a
question that Israel can answer, not me.
Uh, how did they know the locations of
Iran's top generals? Well, some people
are are are saying that the Pakistanis
that the Pakistani fellow, what's his
name? Aim, he met Muhammad Beri. uh one
of the Iranian top generals and Aim
Munir gave a gift to Beri which is a
wristwatch
and apparently the wristwatch had a
tracking device which allowed Israel to
pinpoint Mr. Beri's location which would
indicate that Israel and Pakistan are
allies if that's the case. Of course, I
don't know if it's true, but that's
something I saw on social media just
briefly.
Um, so maybe those hostages don't have
those wrist watches that Israel can
track. Perhaps that's that's the reason.
Okay, I don't know.
Parasidi says, "Why is there no change
in education till now?" Well, I am not
the person who can answer the question.
It's the government of India that can
answer that. We need an education system
revamp. We need reforms, deep and wide
and broad reforms in the Indian
education system.
What reforms? Well, I have laid it out
in great detail in episodes 28 to 31 or
32 of the Ask Abijit Show. I have not
I'm not somebody who complains. I also
give solutions. So, I have given those
solutions. But well, nothing has been
done. Well, it's up to the government of
India. They have they're under no
obligation to listen to me. But I would
love to see some reforms because that's
what the civilization needs. Rashi Kudin
says, "Do you hate Bangladesh? What do
you think personally?" I have absolutely
no hate whatsoever for Bangladesh. Why
would I hate Bangladesh? The people of
Bangladesh genetically are my people. Do
you people of Bangladesh are part of
descendants of the ancient Bangladesh
which goes back thousands of years. Why
would I hate the people of Bangladesh?
The problem
is is the radicaliz radicalization and
the hatred for India that seems to be on
the rise and the hatred for Hindus that
is demonstrable.
So that's unfortunate and that's
something that needs to be addressed.
Beyond that let Bangladesh live its own
life. We will not I mean I have no
hatred for Bangladesh just as I have no
hatred for Pakistan. I know that
Pakistan is our enemy. I know that the
average Pakistani most likely wants
people like Indians and Hindus dead. But
it's also true that the most Pakistanis
are also somehow related to me
genetically and by blood.
So uh I don't hate them personally. I
would love them to have good lives but I
don't want them to be able to kill me.
That's what I'm saying in my people. So
similarly with Bangladesh, I have no
hatred for Bangladesh. Why would I have
it? I would love to see Bangladesh
prosper. The people do well, the country
do well economically etc. But just stop
killing Hindus and stop hating us. Why?
What have we done to hate to deserve the
hate? We gave you freedom. I don't know
what your textbooks are teaching you.
But without the involvement of the
Indian armed forces, Bangladesh would
have never been liberated in 1971 and
the Pakistanis would have I don't know
what they would have done to your
people. Okay, that's what I would say.
Okay, we're going to take just a couple
more questions and then we are done. Uh
how is India going to be like in terms
of war situation? Who does India take as
allies? All neighbors China, Pakistan,
USA against us. India doesn't have
allies which is fine. Nobody has allies.
India doesn't have allies. Okay.
Iran doesn't have allies. Nobody has
allies that way. Um how is India like in
terms of war preparations? I think India
is on a good track. We have tremendous
air defense capabilities. We have good
offensive capabilities in terms of
missiles and I'm sure that we are
focusing on Atmana and and local defense
protection and all. So I think we are on
a very good track in terms of defense
preparedness. Of course we can do more.
We can do more and all and we we should
have a stockpile of tens of thousands of
missiles of various kinds. That's what
I've been saying. Apart from that we
have no allies. Our neighbors are very
nasty. They are all puppets of other
other nations and we have to be prepared
for all all eventualities.
Suchin says had instead Iran toned down
the rhetoric, not sponsored militias,
but stealthily worked on nukes, it would
have in a few years been too powerful to
be bombed. Well, there is some element
of truth to what you're saying. Tone
down the rhetoric, not sponsoring
militias. No, it's always good to have
proxies and allies of various kinds
beyond your borders. And that's one
trick in the book that India is missing.
But do it in a very lowprofile way. And
of course, had they worked on nukes and
developed nukes, well then it would have
been very hard for anybody to um cross
their red lines, right? So yeah, I I
don't know if they have nukes. I still
don't know if they have nukes uh and
what their nuclear doctrine is like in
case they do have nukes. So yeah, it's
all ifs and buts right now. Uh
Tanmay Pun says why did Hitler fail in
the battle of Britain even after
investing so much in the air force.
What happened is that the Americans were
supplying the British. So Hitler had
this massive air force but the British
were churning out aircraft like
sausages.
They were churning off their these
production lines that were churning out
spitfires and whatnot all the time. All
the time all the time and they were
getting supplied by the Americans across
the Atlantic. So that's why despite
being a small island the British were
able to resist and withstand the German
onslaught the blitzk
by the German air force and then Hitler
somehow changed his mind and he turned
his direction turned his gaze to the
USSR and he broke the molotov pact and
decided to launch operation Barbar Roa
and did not did did not do it very well
so Britain got that breathing space so
yeah
from from Hitler's perspective he if he
had finish the job then things would
have been different but of course Hitler
is a very evil guy and a monster so good
it didn't work out that way
Kumar Kanesh says I am I am an aviation
enthusiast I think a pilot's job is one
of the hardest and I can't imagine how
tough it is I feel especially in India
people are not aware of I suppose it is
it's a job with a tremendous amount of
responsibility it's a very complicated
job you're flying a very complex uh
vehicle and yeah most people don't
understand how complicated and and
difficult it is. So yes, I agree. Um
Ritik says I agree. India would not have
been India won't be united if it had not
been colonized. India would not have
been colonized if it was united and so
on. I agree. Right. So okay, thank you
very much everybody. I am at the end of
today's live stream. We are past 3 hours
and 15 minutes. That's tremendously
long. I think I'll need a drink of water
or something else very soon. So, thank
you so much everybody for all your
questions. I really enjoyed this and
we're going to keep on doing this next
week. So, until the next live stream,
please please keep
keep questioning, keep asking questions,
keep thinking critically, keep raising
your standards and I will see you in the
next live stream. Thank you so much
everybody. Take care.